             WORLDS APART
everything—one huge, quiet cave. Narrow, endless passageways betwee 
walls; and resembling houses—dark, ice-encrusted rocks; and in t 
rocks—deep holes glowing crimson; there, in the holes by the fire—squat 
ting people. A light, icy draught blows white dust from under their feet, and 
heard by no one—over the white dust, over the boulders, over the caves 
over the squatting people—the huge, measured tread of some super-mam 
mothish mammoth.



             [from] WE

  Record
  Synopsis: An Announcement / The Wisest of Lines / A Poem
  I am simply transcribing—word for word—what was printed in tie 
State Gazette today:
  "In 120 days the construction of INTEGRAL will be completed. T 
mighty, historical hour is near when the first INTEGRAL will soar into un 
versal space. One thousand years ago, your heroic ancestors subjugated 
entire earthly sphere to the power of the United State. Awaiting you is a, 
even more glorious feat: the integration of the infinite equation of the uni- 
verse by means of the glass, electrical, fire-breathing INTEGRAL. Awaiting 
you is the subjugation of those unknown creatures inhabiting other planets 
to the beneficent yoke of reason—and perhaps still living in a wild state,0 
freedom. If they will not comprehend that we bring them a mathematically 
infallible happiness, our duty is to force them to be happy. But before 
arms—we will attempt words.
  In the name of the Benefactor it is hereby announced to all the numbe 
of the United State:
  Everyone who feels capable is obliged to compose treatises, poems, man
ifestoes, odes or other works, on the beauty and grandeur of the United State 
  This will be the first cargo which the INTEGRAL will carry.
  All hail to the United State, all hail to the numbers, all hail to th
Benefactor!"
  I am writing this—and I feeli.my cheeks are burning. Yes: the integrant 
tion of the grandiose universal equation. Yes: to unbend the wild curve, to 
straighten it out along a tangent—an asymptote—to a straight line. Because 
the line of the United State—is a straight line. A great, divine, precise, wise,. 
straight line—the wisest of lines .. .
  I, D-503, the builder of the INTEGRAL,—I am only one of the mathe7 
maticians of the United State. My pen, accustomed to figures, is not capa

                       Evgeny Ivanovich Zamiatin 417

etween     ble of creating the music of assonances and rhythms. I am merely attempt-
 in the    ing to record what I see, what I think—more accurately, what we think
-squat-    '(thm is it precisely: we, and let this WE be the title of my records). Yet this
 t, and    will be a derivative of our life, of the mathematically perfect life of the
 caves,    'United State, and if that is so, will it actually not be in itself, independent-
r-mam-     y of my will, a poem? It will—that I believe and know.
             I am writing this and I feel: my cheeks are burning. Probably, this is
1920-2)    similar to what a woman experiences when for the first time she senses
i Struve   within herself the pulse of a new—still tiny, blind human being. It is I and

           simultaneously—not I. And for long months it will be necessary to nourish 
           it with one's life fluid, with one's blood, and then—painfully tear it away 
           from oneself and lay it at the feet of the United State.
             But I am ready, just as everyone is,—or almost everyone of us. I am ready.



 in th.      Record 2
             Synopsis: Ballet / Square Harmony / X

:d. The      Spring. From beyond the Green Wall, from the wild invisible plains, the 
►to uni-   wind carries the yellow pollen of some kind of flowers. Your lips grow dry 
ted the    from this sweet pollen—every minute you pass your tongue over them— 
,u is an   and it must be that all the women you meet have sweet lips (and the men 
he uni-    as well, of course). This somewhat hinders logical thinking.
wai tin      But then, what a sky! Blue, unspoiled by a single cloud (what wild 
planets    astes the ancients had if their poets could be inspired by those ugly, disor- 
;tate of   derly, clumsily jostling clumps of vapor). I love—I am certain that I will not 
atically   be mistaken if I say: we love—this same sterile, immaculate sky alone. On 
before     such days—the whole world is cast of that very same immutable eternal 

           glass as the Green Wall, as all of our buildings. On such days you see into 
ambers     he bluest depths of things, you see certain of their amazing equations, hith- 
            to unknown—in something most common, prosaic.
s, man-      Why, just take this example. This morning I was at the launching site 
d State.    here the INTEGRAL is being built—and suddenly I caught sight of the 

            achine benches: with eyes closed, in self-oblivion, the spheres of the reg- 
to the     lators were spinning; flashing, the levers were bending to the right and to 

            e left; the pendulum rod was proudly dipping its shoulders; to the rhythm 
ntegra-     an inaudible music the blade of a tooling lathe bobbed up and down in 
irve, to    dance. I suddenly perceived all the beauty of this grandiose mechanical 
3ecause    ballet suffused with the buoyant azure sun.
t2, wise,    And further—in the same vein: why—beautiful? Why is the dance beau- 
           tiful? Answer: because it was a non free motion, because the whole profound 
mathe-      easing of the dance is precisely in its absolute, aesthetic subordination, in 
rt capa-    ideal nonfreedom. And if it is true that our ancestors would surrender

418         WORLDS APART
themselves utterly to dance during—the most inspired moments of their 1 
(religious mysteries, military parades), then this signified but one thing: from 
time immemorial, the instinct for nonfreedom has been organically inherent 
in man, and in our present-day life—are only consciously ..
 I shall have to finish later: the intercom has clicked. I looked up: 0-90 
of course. In half a minute she herself would be here: to take me for the walk;
 Dear 0!—it always seemed to me—that she resembled her name, 
approximately 10 centimeters shorter than the Maternal Norm—and thn 
seemingly turned so roundly as though on a lathe,—and the pink 0—het 
mouth—opened wide to greet every word of mine. And moreover: tai 
round, plump little fold of skin on the wrist of her hand—the kind that ch 
dren often have.
 When she entered, the logical flywheel was still humming at full force in 
me and because of its momentum I began to talk about the formula I had ju 
constructed which included all of us, as well as the machines and the dance
 "Marvelous. Isn't it?" I asked.
 "Yes, marvelous. Spring," 0-90 gave me a pink smile.
 Well, there, how do you like that: spring . . . She talks about spr n 
Women . . . I fell silent.
 Downstairs. The avenue was full: the post-lunch private hour, in weatlf 
like this—we usually spend on a supplementary walk. As always, the music 
factory was playing the March of the United State with all its pipes. In eve 
ranks, four abreast, solemnly keeping time to the rhythm, the numbers, 
walked—hundreds, thousands of numbers, in pale-blue unifs (probabl*, 
from the ancient Uniforme), with golden badges on their chests—a sta 
number for every male and female. I too—we, the four of us,—were one o 
the countless waves in this mighty torrent. To the left of me was 0-90 (if one 
of my hairy ancestors had been writing this about a thousand years ago-,.7,- 
he probably would have called her by that amusing word my); to the 
right—two other strangers, a female-number and a male-number.
 A sky of blissful blue, minute, toylike suns in each of the badges, faces 
unclouded by the insanity of thoughts . . . Rays of light—you understand: 
everything made of some indivisible, radiant, smiling matter. And the rhyth- 
mic measures of the brass: "Tra-ta-to-tam. Tra-to-ta-tam," those were the 
brass steps gleaming in the sun and with each step—you climbed higher and 
higher, into the dizzy azure.
 And then, just as had been the case that morning, at the launching site 
once again I perceived, as if only then for the first time in my life—I per- 
ceived everything: the absolutely straight streets, the glass pavements shim- 
mering with rays of light, the divine parallelepipeds of transparen 
dwellings, the square harmony of the grayish-blue ranks. To illustrate: it 
was as though not entire generations, but I—yes I alone—had conquered

                                                       Evgeny Ivanovich Zamiatin                                                                                  419
      he old God and the old life, yes, I alone had created all of this, and I, like 
   a tower, I was afraid to move my elbow lest the walls, cupolas, machines 
   collapse in showering fragments . .
            And an instant later—a leap through the centuries, from + to – . I 
   recalled (apparently,—an association by contrast)—I suddenly recalled a 
   painting in a museum: one of their avenues from twentieth-century times, a 
   deafening, motley, jumbled mob of people, wheels, animals, billboards, 
   trees, colors, birds .. . And they do say that it was in fact like that—it could 
   have been so. It seemed to me that it was so unlikely, so absurd, that I lost 
   control and suddenly burst into laughter.
            And immediately there was an echo—laughter—from the right. I 
   turned: before my eyes—white—extraordinarily white and sharp teeth, an 
   :unfamiliar woman's face.
            "Forgive me," she said, "but you were gazing about with such inspira- 
   tion—like some mythological god on the seventh day of creation. It seems 
   to me you are certain that you and nobody else created me as well. I am 
   very flattered . . ."
            All of this—without a smile, I might even say—with a certain deference 
   (perhaps she knew that I was the builder of the INTEGRAL). Yet I could 
   not say—in the eyes or the eyebrows—there was some manner of strange, 
   irritating X and I could not understand it in the least, I could not give it any 
   mathematical expression.
            For some reason I grew embarrassed and with some confusion I began 
   to justify my laughter logically. It was perfectly clear that this contrast, this 
    mpassable abyss between now and then . . .
            "But why— impassable'? (What white teeth!) One can throw a small 
   bridge—over the abyss. Just imagine to yourself: a drum, battalions, 
    anks—that did exist as well—and, consequently . . ."
            "Yes, of course: it's clear," I cried (it was an amazing intersection of 
   thoughts: she—almost with my very same words—what I had recorded 
   before the walk).—You understand: even the thoughts. This was because 
   nobody is one, rather one of. We are so one and the same . ."
            She:
            "Are you certain'?"
            I perceived the brows upturned at a sharp angle towards the temples- 
. like the sharp horns of an X, again I felt bewildered for some reason; I
   glanced to the right, to the left—and . .
            To my right—she, slender, sharp, tensely resilient, like a whip, 1-330 
   (now I saw her number); to the left-0-90, entirely different, all circles, with 
  the childlike fold of skin around her wrist; and on the extremity of our four- 
  some—an unfamiliar male number—double—curved, in the shape of the 
  letter S. We were all different . . .

420        WORLDS APART
  The one on the right, 1-330, apparently caught my distraught look a 
with a sigh:
  "Yes . . . Alas!"
  In essence, this alas was perfectly appropriate. But again there was 
certain something in her face or in her voice .. .
  With an extraordinary sharpness for me—I said "There's no alas abo 
it Science is advancing and clearly—if not now, then in fifty, in a hundr 
years . ."
  "Even all the people's noses . ."
  "Yes, the noses," I was practically shouting now. "As long as there 
is whatever basis for envy ... If 1 have a nose like a button, while some
else . . ."
  "Well, but your nose, forgive me, is even classical, as they said in older; 
times. And your hands there . . . No, do show me, show me your hands1 
I could not bear it when people looked at my hands: they were all hairy, 
shaggy—some kind of absurd atavism. I stretched out my hand and—i 
voice as indifferent as possible—I said:
  "Apelike."
 She glanced at the hands, then at my face: But there is a most curiou 
affinity," she seemed to be weighing me with her eyes, the little horns at th 
corners of her eyebrows appeared fleetingly.
  "He is registered to me," 0-90 opened her mouth in pink joyfulness.
 It would have been better for her to remain silent—it was completely 
irrelevant. In general, this dear 0— . . . how could I say . . . the speed of 
her tongue is incorrectly designed, the speed per second of the tongue 
should always be slightly less than the speed per second of thought, and by 
no means the contrary.
 At the end of the avenue, on the Accumulator Tower, the bell was strik- 
ing a booming 17. The personal hour was ended. 1-330 was leaving together:: 
with that S-shaped male number. He had the kind of face that inspired 
respect, and then 1 saw what seemed to be a familiar face. I had met hitt
somewhere—but then I could not recall.
 Upon leaving, 1-330—still X-like—gave me a wry smile. "Come b 
auditorium 112 the day after tomorrow."
 I shrugged my shoulders:
 "If I am assigned—precisely to that auditorium you have named.. .
 She, with a kind of incomprehensible confidence: "You will be."
 This woman had the same unpleasant effect on me as an insoluble, irra- 
tional component which has made a haphazard intrusion in an equation 
And I was happy to be left alone with dear 0—if only for a short while.
 Arm-in-arm we passed four rows of avenues. At the corner she had to 
turn left, 1—to the right.

                        Evgeny Ivanovich Zamiatin    421

ht look and  "I would like so much to come to you today, to lower the blinds. 
           Especially today, right now . . ." 0-timidly raised her crystal-blue eyes to me.
             She is amusing. Well, what could I say to her? She had been at my place 
 ere was aonly yesterday and she knew as well as I that our next sexual day was the day 
          after tomorrow. This was simply the same case of her "premature thoughts"— 
alas about as happens (at times harmfully) with a premature ignition in a motor.
t hundred    Upon parting I kissed her twice . . no, I shall be precise: three times I 
          kissed those marvelous blue eyes, unspoiled by a single cloudier.

 there — 
someone      Record 3
             Synopsis: A Jacket / A Wall I The Book of Hourly Tables

n olden,     I have looked over everything that I wrote yesterday—and I see: I did 
bands!"   not write with sufficient clarity. That is, all of this is perfectly clear for any 
 hairy,   one of us. But how is one to know: perhaps, you, the strangers, to whom 
3---in a  the INTEGRAL will carry my notes, perhaps, you will have read the great 
          book of civilization only as far as the page that our ancestors did about 900 
          years ago. Perhaps you do not even know such ABC's as the Book of 
urious    Hourly Tables, the Personal Hours, the Maternal Norm, the Green Wall, 
at the    the Benefactor. It seems ridiculous to me—and at the same time very diffi- 
          cult to speak about all this. It would all be the same as though some writer 
ess.      or other, let us say, of the 20th century, were forced to explain in his novel 
letely    what was meant by jacket, apartment, wife. But nevertheless, if his novel is 
ed of     translated for savages—is it really conceivable to avoid annotations con- 
ngue      cerning a jacket?
d by         I am certain that a savage would look at jacket and think: "Well, what 
          is that for? Merely a burden." Jr seems to me that you would look precisely 
rik-       he same way when I told you that since the time of the Two Hundred 
rher      Years' War none of us has been on the other side of the Green Wall.
red          But, dear friends, you must do at least some thinking, it does help a 
rim       great deal. After all, it is clear: all of human history, as much as we know 
          of it, is the history of the transition from nomadic forms to increasingly 
by        sedentary ones. Does it not then follow from this that the most sedentary 
          form of life (ours)—is at the same time the most perfect (ours). If people 
          dashed about the earth from one end to the other, then it was only during 
          prehistoric times when there were nations, wars, commerce, the discoveries 
          of the various Americas. But whatever for, who needs that now?
             I grant you: growing accustomed to this sedentary form did not come 
          immediately or without difficulty. When during the time of the Two 
          Hundred Years' War all the roads were destroyed and became overgrown 
          with grass—for the first while it must have seemed very inconvenient to live 
          in cities, cut off from one another by green jungles. But what of it? After

422                         WORLDS APART
man first lost his tall, he probably did not learn at once how to chase away:     ly the fi 
flies without the aid of that tail. But now—can you imagine yourself—with         authorit 
a tail? Or perhaps you can imagine yourself on the street—naked, without          without 
a jacket (it's possible that you still go strolling about in jackets). Here it is they wo 
precisely the same thing: I cannot imagine to myself a city that is no            eral hist 
enveloped by a Green Wall. I cannot imagine a life that is not arrayed in the     streets a
figured chasubles of The Book of Hourly Tables.                                       1 ca 
    The Tables . . . Right at this very moment the purple figures on a gold       intellige 
en background are gazing sternly and tenderly into my eyes from my wall           a life lil 
I am involuntarily reminded of what among the ancients was called an icon         one, frc 
and I feel the urge to compose verses or prayers (which is one and the same,      der of 
thing). Oh, why am I not a poet that I might sing in worthy praise of you,'::     To mur 
0 Tables, 0 heart and pulse of the United State.                                  years— 
    All of us (and, perhaps, you too), while yet children in school, read this:,, lion yep 
mightiest of monuments to come down to us from ancient literature—VW              ten-yea 
Railroad Timetables. But place even it beside The Tables—and you will see,        a minu 
side by side, graphite and diamond: both have one and the same thing-----C        not on( 
carbon,—but how eternal, how translucent, how the diamond gleams. Whose           entific
spirit would not thrill when you rush headlong with a roar through the page           M4 
of The Railroad Timetables. But the The Tables —actually transform each o         state!) 
us into the steel, six-wheeled hero of a mighty poem. Every morning, with six     much 
wheeled precision, at precisely the same hour and at precisely the same';         orals, I 
minute,—we, millions of us, arise as one At precisely the same hour, millions:    poultr3 
like one, we begin our work—millions like one we finish. And coalescing into      and nc 
a single, million-handed body, at precisely the very same second, designated      breedii 
by The Tables, —we raise our spoons to our mouth,—and at precisely the                It 
very same second we emerge for our walk and we proceed to the auditorium,         afraid: 
to the hall for the Taylor exercises, and we withdraw to sleep .. .               malici 
   I will be entirely frank: even we do not yet have the absolutely precise       have r 
solution to the question of happiness: twice a day—from 16 to 17 and from         a seri(
21 to 22 the single mighty organism dissolves into separate cells: these are          Bh 
what The Tables have designated as—the Personal Hours. During these               Lion ti 
hours you may see: in the rooms of some—the blinds are modestly lowered,          not be 
others, to the slow steps of the March—walk in measured time along the            times 
avenue, while yet others—as I myself am doing right now—are at their desks.       apes, 
But I resolutely believe—let them call me an idealist and a dreamer—I believe:    some' 
sooner or later—but someday we shall find a place in the general formula for      can st
these hours as well, someday all 86,400 seconds will be included in The Book           F 
of Hourly Tables.                                                                 dowr 
   I have had the occasion to read and hear a great deal that was improba-        migh 
ble about those times when people were still living in a free, i.e., unorganized,  bolt- 
wild state. But the most improbable thing always seemed to me to be precise-       rienc

                     Evgeny lvanovich Zarniatin 423
          the following: how in those times—even a rudimentary governmental 
        authority could permit people to live without anything resembling our Tables, 
it      without any obligatory walks, without any precise regulation of mealtimes; 
is      they would get up and go to bed whenever they took it into their heads; sev- 
)t      eral historians even say that apparently in those times lights burned in the 
te      streets all night, people walked and rode along the streets all night.
          I cannot comprehend any of this in the least. However restricted their 
        intelligence might have been, all the same they should have understood that 
        a life like that was the most genuine form of mass murder—albeit a slow 
        one, from day to day. The state (humaneness) prohibited the outright mur- 
        der of a single person and did not prohibit the partial murder of millions. 
        To murder a single person, i.e., to decrease the sum of human lives by 50 
         ears—that was criminal, but to decrease the sum of human lives by 50 mil- 
         'oh years—that was not criminal. Really, is that not ridiculous? Any of our 
          year-old numbers can resolve this mathematical-moral problem in half 
         minute; but they were incapable—with all their Kants together (because 
         tit one of those Kants could hit on the idea of constructing a system of sci- 
         ntific ethics, i.e., based on subtraction, addition, division, multiplication). 
          Moreover—is it really not absurd that a state (it dared to call itself a 
         te!) could leave sexual life without any control. Whoever, whenever and as 
         uch as one wished ... Completely unscientific, like animals. And like ani- 
         Is, blindly, they bore children. Is it not ridiculous: to know horticulture, 
          try-breeding, fish-breeding (we have exact data that they knew all of this) 
         d not know how to proceed to the ultimate step in this logical ladder: child- 
         teding. Not to hit upon the idea of our Maternal and Paternal Norms. 
          It is so ridiculous, so improbable, that now that I have written it I am 
         aid: what if suddenly, you the unknown readers, should take me for a 
          kious jokester. What if suddenly you should think that I simply wish to 
           my joke at your expense and I am relating the most utter rubbish with 
         erious face.
          But first of all: I am not capable of jokes—falsehood is a secret func- 
         n that enters into every joke; and secondly: the United State Science can 
         t be mistaken. And where would any state logic be forthcoming in those 
         es when people lived in a condition of freedom, i.e., like that of animals, 
         es, the herd? What could one demand of them if even in our time—from 
         tnewhere at the bottom, out of the shaggy depths,—a wild, apelike echo 
         Al still be infrequently heard?
          Fortunately—only infrequently. Fortunately—this is only a minor break- 
         Own in details: they can be repaired logically, without halting the eternal, 
         ghty progress of the whole Machine. And for the disposal of the twisted 
         lt—we have the skillful, heavy hand of the Benefactor, we have the expe- 
         nced eyes of the Guardians ..

424                          WORLDS APART

    Yes, by the way, now I remember: that male number from yesterday, th             At this poin 
double-curved one, like S,—it seems to me that I have had occasion to see hi     this point I beca 
coming out of the Bureau of Guardians. Now I understand why I had th             forth out of the 
instinctive feeling of deference towards him and a kind of awkwardness whe         ere in vain (wh 
in his presence that strange number 1-330 . . . I must confess that this I .     assigned here?); 
    The bell is ringing for sleep: 22 1/2. Until tomorrow.                       culty I switched 
                                                                                 gone on to the rr 
                                                                                 mathematician i 
    Record 4                                                                     recently inventec 
    Synopsis: The Savage with the Barometer / Epilepsy /If Only                      "By simply 
    Up until now everything in life had been clear to me (it is hardly b         sonatas in an ho 
chance that I have, apparently, a certain predilection for this very wore        They could crea 
"clear"). But today . . . I do not understand.                                   unknown form ( 
    First of all: I was actually assigned to be precisely in auditorium 112,     of what they pi 
just as she had told me. Although the probability was-                           black box (curt 
                        1,500                      3                             instrument)—th( 
                                                                                 but one more tir 
                    10,000,000                  20,000                              And so fort 
    (1,500—that is the number of auditoria, 10,000,000—represents the            Well, yes, 1 shal 
numbers). Secondly... But better to take it in order.                            grand box—I-3. 
    The auditorium. An enormous hemisphere of glass massifs all suffused         appearance of h(
with sunlight. Circular rows of noble, globe-shaped, closely cropped heads.         She was in a 
My heart gently skipped a beat as I looked all around. I think, I was search     dress, the white 
ing: whether somewhere above the pale-blue waves of unifies a rosy cres-         undulating with 
cent would be glistening—the dear lips of 0—. Then suddenly salmon's             blinding, almost
extraordinarily white and sharp teeth, similar to . . . no, wrong. This evening,    Her smile--; 
at 21, 0- would come to me—the wish to see her here was perfectly natural        Wild, convulsive 
    Then—a bell. We rose, sang the Hymn of the United State—and on the           ow of rational m 
stage appeared the phonolecturer gleaming with wit and a golden loudspeaket      everyone was lai
    "Respected numbers! Archeologists recently unearthed a book from the            Yes, epileps► 
20th century. In it the ironical author tells of a savage and a barometer. The   bite—if only it v 
savage noted: every time when the barometer came to rest on rain—it actu-        the Sun. But not 
ally rained. And since the savage felt like rain, he then began to remove the    glass bricks—no 
right amount of mercury so that the level stopped at rain (on the screen—a      everything into t
savage in feathers, shaking out the mercury: laughter). You laugh: but does         The number 
it not seem to you that the European of that era is more deserving of your      and snickered. E 
laughter. Like the savage, the European also wanted rain,—but rain with a       microscopic but 
capital letter, an algebraic rain. Yet he stood before the barometer like a wet sobered me. I wk.
hen. The savage, at least, had more daring and energy and—even though a             Like everyor 
savage—more logic: he was able to ascertain that there was a connection         I was laughing. I 
between effect and cause. Shaking out the mercury he was able to take the       depicting that wj
first step on that mighty road by which . . ."                                      With what

                                      Evgeny Ivanovich Zamiatin            425

 rom yesterday, the     At this point (I repeat: I am writing without concealing anything)—at 
 )ccasion to see him this point I became seemingly impervious to the vivifying streams pouring 
 nd why I had that   forth out of the loudspeakers. It suddenly seemed to me that I had come 
 wkwardness when     here in vain (why in vain and how could I have not come once I had been 
 ass that this I .   assigned here?); it all seemed to me—hollow, only a shell. And with diffi- 

                     culty I switched my attention back on only when the phonolecturer had 
                     gone on to the main theme: to our music, to mathematical composition (the 
                     mathematician is the cause, the music is the result), to a description of the 
 sy /If Only         recently invented musicometer.
                        "By simply turning this handle, anyone of you can produce up to three 
 le (it is hardly by sonatas in an hour. Yet how difficult that was for your ancestors to achieve. 
Dr this very word    They could create only by driving themselves into fits of inspiration—an 

                     unknown form of epilepsy. And here is a most amusing illustration for you 
 auditorium 112,     of what they produced,—the music of Scriabin—the 20th century. This 
                     black box (curtains parted on the stage and there—their most ancient 
                     nstrument)—they called this box a piano or a royal grand, which shows 
                     but one more time to what extent their music . . ."
                       And so forth—again I do not remember, quite possibly because .. . 
i0--represents the   Well, yes, 1 shall say it straight: because she had walked up to the royal 
                     grand box—I-330. No doubt I was simply struck by this unexpected 
lassifs all suffused appearance of her on the stage.
Ay cropped heads.      She was in a fantastic costume of the ancient era: a tightly fitting black 
link, I was search-  dress, the white of her bare shoulders and bosom sharply defined, and 
nifies a rosy cres-  ndulating with her breathing that warm shadow between . . . and the 
iuddenly salmon's    blinding, almost wicked lips ..
.ong. This evening,    Her smile—a bite, directed here—below. She sat down, began to play. 
; perfectly natural. Wild, convulsive, motley, like their entire life in those times,—not a shad- 
State—and on the     ow of rational mechanicalness. And, of course, they, around me, were right: 
olden loudspeaker.   everyone was laughing. Only a few . . . but why me as well—me?
d a book from the      Yes, epilepsy—a spiritual illness—a pain . . . A slow, sweet pain—a 
I a barometer. The   bite—if only it would go deeper yet, more painfully yet. And then, slowly 
t on rain—it actu-   the Sun. But not ours, not the azure crystalline and uniform one through the 
gan to remove the    glass bricks—no: a wild, soaring, scorching Sun—off with everything—rip 
(on the screen—a     everything into tiny shreds.
at laugh: but does     The number sitting beside me on the left glanced sideways—at me— 
deserving of your    and snickered. For some reason I have a very clear memory of that: I saw a 
,—but rain with a    microscopic bubble of saliva form on his lips and burst. That bubble 
rometer like a wet   sobered me. I was—myself again.
d—even though a        Like everyone else —I heard only the absurd, fussy squeaking of strings. 
was a connection     was laughing. I felt light and simple. The talented phonolecturer had been 
ts able to take the  depicting that wild era too vividly for us—that was all there was to it. 
                       With what pleasure I listened to our contemporary music afterwards.

  426                        WORLDS APART
 (It was demonstrated in conclusion—for contrast.) The crystalline chromat- 
 ic progressions of merging and diverging series—and the summarizing 
 chords of Taylor McLauren; the full-bodied / full-toned, squarely massive 
 passages of the Pythagorean theorem; the mournful melodies of a fading 
 oscillatory movement; the brilliant measures alternating with Frauenhofer's 
 lines in the pauses —the spectral analysis of the planets... What grandeur! 
 What unwavering equilibrium: And how pitiful—totally unrestricted by 
 anything other than wild fantasies —that willful music of the ancients...
     As usual, in even ranks, four abreast, everyone exited through the wide
 doors of the auditorium. The familiar double-curved figure flitted past me;    To
 I nodded respectfully.                                                         drei
     Dear 0— was supposed to come in an hour I felt pleasantly and, usefully    wet
 excited. Home—quickly to the desk, I handed the duty clerk my pink ticket      thic
 and received a permit for the right to use the blinds. We have this right—     clez
 only for Sexual Days. Otherwise amid our transparent walls seemingly           bet
woven of sparkling air—we always live in full view, eternally washed by the     wai
light. We have nothing to hide from one another. Moreover it facilitates the 
burdensome and exalted labor of the Guardians. Otherwise who can say            bar 
what might happen. It is possible that it was precisely those strange, opaque   it V 
dwellings of the ancients that gave birth to that pitiful cellular psychology   wa 
of theirs. "My [sic!] home is my castle"—it really must have cost them an       De4 
effort to think that one up!                                                    kin
    At 22 I lowered the blinds —and at that very minute 0—entered slightly 
out of breath. She held out her tiny pink mouth to me—and her pink ticket. I 
tore off the coupon—and then I could not tear myself away from that pink        wit 
mouth until the very last moment-22:15.                                         rivi 
    Then I showed her my records and I talked—very well, I thought about        but 
the beauty of the square, the cube, the straight line. She listened so enchant- col 
ingly and pinkly—and suddenly from her blue eyes a teat; a second, a            net 
third,—straight onto the opened page (p. 7). The ink ran. Well, now I shall     lot
have to recopy it.
    "Dear D-, if only you would—if only . . ."
    Well, what if only? What about if only? Again her old refrain: a child. 
Or, perhaps, something new—concerning. . . concerning that other one? 
Even if it were . . . No, that would be too absurd.                             frc
                                                                                SR(
    [the novel continues with 36 more "Records", ed.]                           str 
                                                                 (1920)         wz 
                                                   Translated by S. Cioran      wi 
                                                                                all 
                                                                                ea:

