              NIKOLAI F. FYODOROV
                     1892















         KARAZIN: 
   METEOROLOGIST OR METEORURGE?
 In this essay we will talk about Karazin, a man of many talents, 
not as a meteorologist but as a meteor-urge. The difference between 
a meteorologist and a meteorurge may be defined as follows: the 
ultimate objective of the first is to predict famine, and the second takes 
as his task — and incidentally, only as the first step of the task — salvation 
from famine. Unfortunately, the word urge was corrupted by mystics 
and acquired the connotation of witchcraft — arcane, supernatural acts, 
unseen influences of spirits — and not the clear, open, comprehensive 
exercise of reason on the blind forces of nature.
 While attempting to manufacture saltpeter, an idea occurred to 
Karazin: potassium nitrate could be made with electricity captured 
from the atmosphere's highest strata by specially constructed balloons, 
which would be anchored to the earth with metallic cables. On the 
9th of April, 1814, Karazin wrote about this to Arakcheyev, residing 
in Paris at that time. Among other matters, he mentioned: "If the

32                      Red Star TalesKarazin: Meteorologist or Meteorurge?                                                           33
experiment, as I hope, conclusively confirms my hypothesis about           concentration of electricity — that the highest strata of the atmosphere 
extracting electricity from the stratosphere, it will signal the invention "consist of a perpetual upheaval, like a sea in stormy weather, from 
of a new, unprecedented weapon in the hands of humankind. Water, air,      the arriving and departing oscillations of electric currents.... Why is 
fire, muscles of living beings, tension, and expansion of certain bodies   it impossible to think that humanity can tame electric power as it has 
are still considered to be regulated by natural forces, some of which      tamed animals, water, wind, and fire? It all depends on reaching the 
we have managed to harness and replicate in machines. Consider,            source of the power and creating a channel for directing it for this 
your excellency, the consequences of mastering the massive amount          or that purpose, according to our will. But the source in this case is 
of electrical energy scattered throughout the atmosphere and bending       the farthest height of the atmosphere; metallic cables may serve as the 
it to our will." Subsequently Karazin expresses hope that through the      channels, and balloons as anchors for holding down the ends of the 
medium of electricity, humans "will attain the ability to determine the    cables at a constant height." Recalling the salient chemical properties 
state of the atmosphere, producing rain at will." Intrigued, "Arakcheyev   of electricity, Karazin warns that "the largest electric machine, clad in 
showed Karazin's letter to the renowned chemist Chaptal, an expert in      strips of metal foil and sailing through the heights of the atmosphere, 
the production of saltpeter, who unconditionally approved its contents."   will be a child's toy vis-a-vis a mid-sized zeppelin, comparable with a 
This opinion was echoed by the committee that Prince Gorchakov,            miniature model sailboat set against an English battleship on its course. 
head of the Ministry of Defense, appointed in 1815 in order to review      Man in all his ingenuousness can never replicate the immeasurable scale 
Karazin's proposal of creating condensed explosives and saltpeter          of nature. He can only hope to discover the best ways to implement 
for military purposes. Professor Scherer, a chemist and member of          her resources." That is to say, humanity is not meant to compete 
the Imperial Academy of Sciences, responded to the committee that          with nature, but only to regulate her. "Experiments conducted with 
"according to his own observations, which he intended to publish, he       the proposed equipment will undoubtedly be astounding. The results 
saw no other explanation for the creation of potassium nitrate, even in    may include the following. 1) The most accurate information about 
the usual course of producing saltpeter, than the effect of atmospheric    the factors of changing atmospheric conditions. This data, combined 
electricity. Finally, Karazin managed to get the attention of His          with general meteorological observations, would open the way for 
Majesty Alexander Pavlovich himself, to whom Karazin conveyed              transforming meteorology into an exact science, i.e., a science as 
a note about meteorology during the latter's tour through Kharkov          capable of calculating and predicting the weather in given places at 
in September 1817. His Royal Highness was particularly taken by            given times as astronomy is accurate in predicting eclipses.... Our 
the following words in the note: "The implementation of electricity        country has a distinct advantage in realizing this vision.... No other 
from higher atmospheric strata for the benefit of humankind. The           kingdom is endowed with such breadth and variety of landscapes for 
important invention presented herewith could be applied only at a          conducting such experiments as our Russia. 2) The achievements 
small scale due to the inadequacy of resources. It accords with our        of chemistry and technology... In the north, manufacturing and 
age and Russia's glorious position within it. As a patriot, it would be    industry will be powered naturally by harnessing the sun's energy. 3) 
 a pity for me to see a foreigner stumble upon this very same idea."       Benefits of land management." This proposal was forwarded to the 
 In response to the sovereign's request for further elaboration, Karazin   academy of sciences, where Nikolai Fuss interpreted its contents at 
 submitted a new document in which he proposed — based on the              the members' conference. Fuss concluded that quite a few methods 
 fact that the higher one ascends in the atmosphere, the higher the        already existed for harnessing electricity in amounts sufficient "for

34                       Red Star Tales                                                  Karazin: Meteorologist or Meteorurge?          35

fulfilling all technical demands," and that "most, if not all, of Karazin's captives in the rhythms of urban life, have lost the ability to understand
supposed predictions were nothing more than hypotheses without any          the meaning of the interdependence between sentient beings and the blind,
proof." Therefore the 20,000 rubles Karazin had deemed necessary for        unfeeling jo- rces of nature. And this interdependence — which we are
conducting his experiments "would be spent in vain," Fuss concluded.        compelled to acknowledge as unavoidable, preordained, superseding 
Although precisely this conclusion was marked by an anonymous               all the achievements and vanities of modern man — is the primal 
penciled comment — "Russia won't go very far on Fusses like these"          riddle that humanity, whether consciously or unconsciously, has been 
— nevertheless Fuss' opinion prevailed, and Karazin's project, which        attempting to solve. In antiquity, the awareness of the meaning of 
would have provided humanity with real power to eradicate suffering,        this interdependence was encoded in the myth of the Sphinx, which 
remained untested. Incidentally, "a project for manufacturing an acid       asked passers-by to solve riddles; the wrong answer would cost the 
to power Leppikh's zeppelin, capable of carrying enough passengers          human interlocutor his life, while the Sphinx would die if the riddle 
and explosives to blow up all the fortifications or personnel of the        was solved. As the whole of humankind is about to face the Sphinx, 
greatest military powers" was awarded 40,000 rubles.                        it is consequently obliged to work towards a solution to the riddle, 
   Thus "the representatives of Russian science conclusively rejected       i.e. to marshal all its current resources and seek additional ones in 
the Karazin proposal; they did not notice what was original and             order to resolve its differences with the blind, intractable forces of 
productive about it." It is worth noting that Karazin's thoughts stood      nature that herald nothing but death in all its different manifestations. 
so far out of the mainstream that they may even be inaccessible to our      Intractable nature, precisely because it is intractable, is an agent of 
contemporaries. Theories and projects pertaining to Karazin's areas         death; ignorance is the gravest sin, punishable by death. However, 
of interest are viewed suspiciously by, and elicit scant response from,     as darkness and gloom melt away before light, this blind force will 
the worldly trade and industrial sectors that hold the public captive       disappear when light floods each and every human life emerging on 
and condition it to such an extent that people cannot conceive of a         earth — instead of remaining limited to a small minority, where it 
common task to rally around; they are in fact repelled by any task that      loses its innate properties and appears as a mere gleam. As long as 
requires collective effort; after all, Karazin's plans would have required   one social group commands some knowledge without possessing 
exactly such a collective effort involving everyone, all of humanity         any power, and the other wields some power but remains largely 
from all walks of life.                                                      ignorant, the knowledge of the former will not be genuinely capable of 
   Considering that the military has recently begun to incorporate           regulating power, while the blind actions of the latter will necessarily 
aircraft, it would be easy to attach the equipment proposed by               be ineffective and repetitive despite all humankind's pride at possessing 
Karazin to the existing infrastructure to carry out experiments. But         so-called cognition, which hardly deserves its name. A spark from the 
I doubt if we will have the patience to await the results; in order to       electrical generator may have all the properties of a lightning bolt, its 
eliminate errors and arrive at the correct conclusions in projects such      crackle may possess the characteristics of thunder, but producing this 
as Karazin's, it is first necessary to apprehend the genuine importance      tiny discharge does not make us Jupiters or free us from that deity's 
of its subject matter. Alas, in Karazin's own words, "the relevance of       power. Even Karazin's brand of redirecting thunder, when it becomes 
the subject may not be fully comprehensible to ordinary citizens and          ubiquitous and is carried out according to plan, will only be a step, the 
bevies of magazine critics," i.e. neither to those who are expected           first step, towards the regulation of blind meteorological processes of 
to make reasonable judgments nor to those who, living in cities and           the planet.

36                     Red Star Tales                                              Karazin: Meteorologist or Meteorurge?       37


  Humanity is faced with two choices. Acknowledge that life is         American method of creating rain with explosives, but also Karazin's 
evil and aim towards self-destruction (Buddhism), or, if life is good, project, and all the other ways of acting on nature that will emerge as 
then within this acknowledgment lies the motivation for restoring      soon as they receive the close, intensive attention long due to them.

it, which is exactly the same as the Christian tenet of resurrection; 
surely the goal of transforming the blind forces of famine, plague,                                          First published in Russian: 1892 
                                                                                                             Translation by Anindita Banerjee
and death into life-affirming ones should unite all of us. To consider 

destruction good (as Count L. N. Tolstoy preaches) is the same as 

believing that there is no good; it is equivalent to Buddhism, which 

considers life evil; this means renouncing Christianity, which only 

the most ignorant would confuse with Buddhism.

  The very forces of nature ask to be regulated by humans, and 

show them where to begin this task. As long as maritime powers, 

originating in countries with temperate climates and nurturing skies, 

dominated world history, the question of regulating meteorological 

phenomena could remain on the margins; but from the moment 

when land-based powers with extreme climates that fluctuate 

suddenly between drought and cloudbursts entered the scene, this 

question began to demand a solution. And if in Russia it had not 

emerged at the center of attention until now, this was only because 

we lived under the epistemological yoke of countries for which it 

was not urgent. Moreover, the solution demands methods and 

approaches that are not available to our role models. It is necessary 

to change the very foundations of producing knowledge and make 

the new paradigms universal, omnipresent, and eternal, to unify all 

experimental knowledge into one. Fortunately, while blind nature, 

afraid of its own extinction, begs for the unification of all rational 

 forces — and rational forces, armed with weapons of mass destruction, 

 unwillingly consider both the imperative of disarmament and its 

 impossibility — the opportunity arises to remake the greatest evil into 

 the greatest good. People who can band together to fight in the army, 

 i.e., as a unified mass according to a given plan, can easily fulfill the 

 primary criteria of a great common task: ubiquity and universality. 

 The only remaining step is to bring meteorological observations 

 into the sphere of peaceable military exercises, to test not only the

