                    Alexander Alexandrovich Bogdanov 
                                           IMalinovskyl 
                                         (1873-1928)

                                           Red Star

                               [The Flight to Mars. Abridged]

                                    CHAPTER V: DEPARTURE
  . . . My attention was involuntarily devoted to the exciting and immine
 moment of our take-off. I watched the snowy surface of the lake which la 
 before us and a beetling granite cliff behind us, expecting a sudden shoe 
 and their sudden disappearance as we ascended. But nothing like this hap 
pened at all.
      Silently, slowly, with a barely perceptible motion, the snow-covere& 
landscape began to leave us. For several seconds I was not aware that we 
had risen at all.
      "The rate of increase is two centimeters," said Menni.
      I understood what this meant. In the first second we were to move o e 
centimeter, in the second—three centimeters, in the third—five centimeters, 
in the fourth—seven centimeters; thus our speed was to be constantly 
changing, at an arithmetically progressive rate. Within a minute we would 
reach the speed of a walking man, in fifteen minutes that of an expres 
train, and so on. < . . . > The ground was rapidly leaving us and the hoar 
zon expanding. The dark masses of the cliffs and the villages were dimin- 
ishing and the outlines of the lakes could be seen as on a map. The sky was 
becoming constantly darker; at the same time that the dark blue band of the 
unfrozen sea claimed the entire western horizon my eyes began to distin- 
guish the brighter stars even with a noon-day sun in the sky.
      The very slow spinning of the spaceship around its vertical axis made 
it possible for us to see space in all directions.
      It seemed that the horizon was rising with us and Earth's surface below us 
appeared as a huge slightly convex dish with decorations provided by the 
Earth's relief. But their outlines became more blurred, the contours flatter, and 
the whole landscape appeared more and more like a geographic map, sharply 
delimited in its center but vague indefinite at the periphery where it was draped 
in a semi-transparent, bluish fog. And the sky had become absolutely black and 
innumerable stars, even the most minute, shown down on us with their steady 
unwinking light, unafraid of the sun whose rays had become painfully hot.

            Alexander Alexandrovich Bogdanov 54
   "Tell me, Menni, will that two-centimeter rate of increase at which we 
are now moving continue for our entire journey?"
   "Yes," he answered, "but half way through our trip it will be reversed 
and every second our speed will decrease by the same measurement. Thus, 
although the greatest speed of the spaceship will be about 2,000 miles an 
hour and the average speed about 1,000 miles an hour, at the moment of 
arrival it will be as slight as at the beginning of our journey, and without any 
shock or strain we will drop onto the surface of Mars. Without this great 
and variable speed we would not be able to reach either Earth or Venus 
because at their closest point-40 million or 65 million miles respectively— 
at the speed of, say, one of your trains, the journey would require centuries, 
not months as does ours. As to the possibility of a "cannon shot" such as I 
have read about in one of your science fiction novels, that would be only a 
joke, because in accordance with the laws of mechanics, to be inside a shell 
when it is fired would be the same as having the shell fired at you."
   "But how have you achieved such a smooth deceleration and accel- 
eration?"
   "The motive force of the spaceship is provided by a radioactive sub- 
stance which we have acquired in great amounts. We have found a method 
for increasing its radiation by a hundred thousand times; this occurs with- 
in the motors with the help of relatively simple electrical and mechanical 
devices. This procedure releases an enormous amount of energy. The parti- 
cles of the radiating atoms disperse, as you know, at a speed which is tens 
of thousands greater than that of an artillery shell. When these particles 
issue from the spaceship in one direction, that is, through a channel with 
impenetrable walls, the spaceship moves in the opposite direction, as in the 
recoil of a gun. In accordance with the laws of motion you can calculate 
that the smallest part of a milligram of such particles in a second's time is 
fully capable of giving our spaceship its steady and variable movement."
   While we were conversing all the other Martians left the room. Menni 
asked me to join him for lunch in his cabin and I left with him. His cabin 
was located against the outer wall of the spaceship and it had a large win- 
dow. We continued with our conversation. I knew that soon I would expe- 
rience a new feeling of weightlessness and I asked Menni about this.
   "Yes," said Menni, "although we are still attracted to the sun, this force 
is insignificant. Tomorrow or the day after, the influence of Earth will also 
be imperceptible. Thanks only to the spaceship's constantly increasing speed 
we will retain 1/400 or 1/500 of our former weight. When this first happens 
it is not easy to make the adjustment, although the change will come very 
slowly. As you acquire lightness, you will lose your agility and make many 
incorrect calculations as you move so that you will commit many clumsy 
errors. The pleasure of soaring through the air will be of doubtful worth. As

            NT vilL113 meami
regards unavoidable palpitation of the heart, dizziness, and nausea, Nett 
will be able to help you You will also have difficulties with water and other 
fluids, which will escape from their containers when even slightly jarred and 
disperse in the form of spherical drops in the air. But we have taken strenu.,  
ous efforts to prevent these inconveniences: furniture and dishes are fastened  
down, fluids are stored in closed containers, and there are handles and straps  
everywhere in case of sudden movements or falls. But you will become 
accustomed to these inconveniences; there is plenty of time."
 Two hours had elapsed since our departure, and weight loss had already 
become rather perceptible, although it was still only something of a game; my 
body had become lighter and my movements freer, but nothing more We had 
left Earth's atmosphere completely by now, but this was no cause for concern 
because there was an adequate supply of oxygen in our sealed airship. The 
segment of Earth's surface which we could see was now exactly like a gear 
graphic map—true, with a measure of distortion: larger in the center, reduced 
toward its edges; here and there it was covered with white puffs of clouds. hi  
the south beyond the Mediterranean Sea, Northern Africa and Arabia could, 
be seen rather clearly through a blue haze; on the north beyond Scandinavia 
the view was lost in a waste of snow and ice—only the cliffs of Spitzbergen 
showed dark. In the east beyond the greenish brown mass of the Urals, cut 
here and there by patches of snow, began a great white kingdom, at places 
with a greenish tint—a faint reminder of the great Siberian coniferous forests. 
To the west beyond the clear outlines of Central Europe the shores of England 
and Northern France were lost in clouds. I found myself unable to watch this 
grand picture for long, because the enormous void below us rapidly evoked a 
feeling in me close to fainting. I renewed my conversation with Menni.
 "Then are you the captain of this craft?" Menni nodded and said:
 "But that doesn't mean that I have the power of a commanding officer. 
It simply means that I have the most experience flying spaceships and my 
orders are accepted, the same way that I accept the astronomical calcula- 
tions which Sterni makes, or as we accept Netti's medical advice because we 
want to retain our health and strength."
 "How old is Dr. Netti? He seems very young to me."
 "I don't remember, sixteen or seventeen," Menni answered with a smile. 
 That is about what I thought and I was astonished at such learning at 
his young age.
 "A doctor at his age!" I burst out.
 "And a proficient and experienced doctor at that," Menni added.
 At the time I did not realize—and Menni intentionally said nothing 
about it—that Martian years were almost twice as long as ours: Mars' rota- 
tion around the sun requires 686 days and at sixteen Martian years of age 
Netti was about thirty years old by Earth time.

             Alexander Alexandrovich Bogdanov 543

                CHAPTER VI: THE SPACESHIP
   After breakfast Menni led me on a tour of our "craft." First we visited 
 the engine room. It occupied the lowest floor of the spaceship directly above 
 its flattened base, and was divided by partitions into five rooms, one in the 
 center and four accessory rooms. The engine stood in the center of the largest 
 room and around it on four sides were round glass-covered windows in the 
 floor, one dear, the three others of various colors; the glass was an inch thick 
 and very pure. At any given time we could see only a part of Earth's surface.
   The heart of the engine was a vertical metal cylinder about ten feet high 
 and two feet in diameter, made, as Menni explained to me, out of a very 
 dense precious metal related to platinum. Within this cylinder the radiation 
 process took place; a panel six inches thick which glowed red with heat tes- 
 tified powerfully to the energy released by this process. But still it was not 
 excessively warm in the room: the entire cylinder was surrounded by a dou- 
 ble shell of some kind of a transparent substance which insulated the sur- 
 roundings from its heat; above, one of the shells was connected to pipes 
 through which the heated air flowed in all directions to warm the spaceship.
   The remainder of the engine connected in various ways with the cylin- 
 der—electric coils, batteries, dials, etc.--surrounded it in an attractive fash- 
 ion and the technician on duty, thanks to a system of mirrors, could watch 
 them all without leaving his chair.
   Of the accessory rooms one was an astronomical observatory, to its left 
 and right were rooms for water and oxygen storage, while opposed to them 
 on the opposite side was the calculating room. In the observatory the floor 
 and the outer wall were of polished optical glass. They were so transparent 
 that when I walked with Menni over the catwalks and decided to glance 
 downward, I saw nothing between me and the void below us—and I had to 
 close my eyes to end the excruciating giddiness. I kept my eyes to the side 
 on the devices which were located in the spaces between the catwalks on 
 complex frameworks suspended from the room's ceiling and internal walls. 
 The major telescope was about six feet long but with a disproportionately 
 large lens and, apparently also, increased powers of magnification.
   "We use only diamond lenses" said Menni. "They provide the largest 
 possible field of observation."
   "What is the power of that telescope?" I asked.
   "About 600x," Menni answered. "But when this is inadequate, we 
photograph the field of observation and examine the photograph under a 
microscope. This method provides a magnification up to 60,000 times and 
more; the photographic process takes not more than a minute's time."
   Menni suggested I look into the telescope to see Earth which we had 
abandoned. He focused the lens himself.

 544        WORLDS APART
  "We are now at a distance of about 1,200 miles," he said. "No 
 you recognize what you have in front of you?"
  I immediately identified the Gulf of. Finland which I had navigated ma 
 times in the service of the Party ... I could see ships at anchor. With a 
 of a lever on the telescope, Menni replaced the eyepiece with a camera, 
 a second later he removed it in its entirety and placed it in a large pied 
 equipment standing to one side which turned out to be a microscope.
  "We are developing and fixing the photograph in the microscope with 
 touching the film," he explained, and after a few minor operations, a half mai 
later, he offered me the microscope's eyepiece. With startling clarity I saw a f
iar steamship belonging to the Northern Company as though it were only a‘few 
feet away from me; the photograph seemed to have depth and natural cob 
although it was translucent. On the bridge stood the gray-haired captain 
whom I had talked a number of times. A sailor who was lowering a large co 
tamer onto the deck was caught as he moved, as well as a passenger who was 
pointing out something with his hand. And we were 1,200 miles away ...
  A young Martian, Sterni's aide, entered the room. He was to make 
precise measurement of the distance covered by the spaceship. We did 
wish to disturb him and we left for the water storage room. Here was 
large container with fresh water and equipment for purifying it A host o 
pipes transmitted this water throughout the spaceship.
  Next came the calculating room. Here stood a multitude of machin 
with dials and gauges unknown to me. Sterni was working at the largest, 
piece of equipment. A long tape stretched out of it, no doubt the results:o 
Sterni's calculations; but the symbols on it, as on the dials, were unknown t 
me. I had no desire to disturb Sterni or even to talk with him. We quicld 
passed into the last accessory room.
  This was the oxygen room in which were stored more than twenty fly 
tons of oxide compounds from which more than 10,000 cubic yards 
oxygen could be extracted when needed; that quantity was sufficient fo 
several journeys such as ours. The equipment necessary for the extraction:: 
of the oxygen was also located here. Here, too, was stored a supply <o 
barites and caustic potassium for removing the carbon dioxide from the air, 
as well as sulphur anhydrides to remove excessive moisture and harmful 
gases. Dr. Netti was in charge of this room.
  Then we returned to the central engine room and from there in a small 
elevator we went straight to the spaceship's upper floor. Here was located a 
second observatory identical with the first one, but with a glass roof rather 
than a floor and larger telescopes. From this observatory we could see the 
other half of space as well as the planet which was our destination. Mars, 
slightly out of the zenith, glowed red. Menni turned a telescope on it and I 
could easily see the outlines of the continents, seas, and canal system which

            Alexander Alexandrovich Bogdanor 545
I knew from Schiaparelli's maps. Menni photographed the planet and under 
the microscope a more detailed map emerged. But I could understand noth- 
ing on it without Menni's explanation: cities, forests, and lakes could only 
be distinguished from one another by distinctions which were impercepti- 
ble and incomprehensible to me.
   "How far away are we?" I asked.
   "Now we are relatively close—about sixty five million miles."
   "Why isn't Mars at the observatory's zenith? Are we flying obliquely to 
 t, and not directly?"
   "Yes, we have no choice. When we left Earth as the result of inertia we 
retained its motive speed around the sun—about 1,200 miles an hour. But 
Mars' speed is only about 960 miles an hour, and if we were to fly perpen- 
dicularly to both their orbits we would hit the surface of Mars with a lat- 
eral speed of 240 miles an hour. This would be very awkward and we must 
select a curving route which equalizes the excess lateral speed."
   "In this case how long will our route be?"
   "About 120 million miles, which will require not less than two and a 
half months' travel time."
   If I had not been a mathematician these numbers would have meant 
nothing to me. But now I felt almok as though I had been caught up in 
some nightmare and I was eager to leave the calculating room.
   Six lateral compartments of the spaceship's upper segment which sur- 
rounded the observatory totally lacked windows and their ceiling, which 
was part of the spherical skin of the spaceship, descended to the floor. In 
that ceiling were located large reserves of "negative-matter" whose repul- 
sion to the earth counter-balanced the weight of the whole spaceship.
   The intermediate floors—numbers two and three—were occupied by 
lounges, individual laboratories, living quarters, toilets, a library, an exer- 
cise room, etc.
   Netti's room was next to mine.

                 CHAPTER VII: PEOPLE
   My loss of weight was constantly more apparent and the increasing feel- 
ing of lightness was no longer pleasant. It was accompanied with a certain 
uneasiness and vague restlessness. I left for my room and lay on my bunk. 
   After an hour or two of immobility and serious thought I impercepti- 
bly drifted into sleep. When I awoke Netti was sitting in my room next to 
the table. Involuntarily I sat up in bed, and as though something had thrown 
me I hit my head against the ceiling.
   "You must. be more careful when you weigh less than twenty pounds," 
Netti said in a genial voice.

546         WORLDS APART
  He had come to see me with the special purpose of giving me advice 
the case of "sea-sickness" which I already felt as the result of loss of weight 
There was a special alarm in my cabin which I could employ to summon; 
him if his help were needed.
  I utilized the opportunity to talk with the young doctor—someth' 
attracted me to this appealing, very learned, but very vivacious lad. I asked 
how it had happened that he alone of all the Martians, with the exception 
of Menni, knew my language.
  "There's a very simple explanation," he explained. When we were 
searching for a human, Menni chose himself and me to visit your country 
and we spent more than a year there until we were able to conclude our 
business with you."
  "That is to say, others were `searching for a human' in other countries` 
as well?"
  "Certainly, they searched among all the major peoples of the world. 
But, as Menni foresaw, we found him first of all in your country, where peo 
ple live most vigorously and vividly and where they must look to the future 
more than others. When we had found our human, we notified the others; 
they gathered together from all over the world and then we left."
  "What do you really mean, when you say you were 'searching for a 
human' or 'found a human'? I realize that you were seeking a subject who 
could play a certain role, as Menni explained to me. I am very flattered to see 
that you chose me, but I would like to know too what you expect from me.
  "I can tell you that, in general terms. We needed a human who pos- 
sessed so far as it was possible the traits of good health and sturdiness, a 
capacity for intellectual labor, few personal ties on Earth, and a weak sense 
of his own individualism. Our physiologists and psychologists assumed that 
the transformation from your society, sharply divided by incessant internal 
warfare, to ours which is organized, as you would say, socialistically, would 
be a very difficult change for any individual and would require a very spe- 
cial personality. Menni decided that you came closer than anyone else."
  "And did all of you accept Menni's opinion?"
  "Yes, we all have complete trust in his analysis. He is a man of exception- 
al mental powers and insight, and he is rarely wrong. He has had more expe- 
rience with humans than any of us; it was he who established our contact."
  "And who was it that established the method of interplanetary commu- 
nication?"
  "That was the result of many individuals' labor, and not one man's. 
`Negative-matter' was first obtained several decades ago. At first it was pro-  
duced only in insignificant quantities, and it required the efforts of many 
workers to find and develop methods for producing it in large amounts. Then 
it was necessary to perfect a technique for obtaining a decomposing radioac-

           Alexander Alexandrovich Bogdanov 541
tive material so we would have an effective engine for our spaceship. That 
also required a great effort. Then, there were many problems resulting from 
the difficult conditions of space travel with its terrible cold and burning sun- 
light not tempered by Earth's atmosphere. The calculations necessary for the 
journey also turned out to be not an easy task and presented difficulties which 
no one had foreseen. In a word, former expeditions ended with the death of 
all their participants until Menni succeeded in organizing the first successful 
flight. But, now, by employing his methods we recently reached Venus, too."
   "If that's so, then Menni is a great man," I added.
   "Yes, if you wish to give that title to a man who can indeed work long 
and well."
   "That's not what I meant: ordinary people, those who take instruc- 
tions, can work long and well. But Menni is obviously something else: he is 
a genius, a creative talent who has invented something new and thus led 
humanity forward."
   "That's not clear, and it seems to me, it's not true. Every workman is 
creative, but it is humanity and the world which create in that workman's 
form. Isn't it true that Menni possesses in his hands all the experience of the 
preceding generations as well as that of contemporary scientists and wasn't 
this the source of all of his discoveries? And wasn't it the world which 
granted him all the elements and the germs of his new ideas? And weren't 
all the stimuli for these ideas the result of a struggle between humanity and 
its world? Man is a person, but his work is impersonal. Sooner or later he 
will die with all his joys and sorrows, but his work remains as part of the 
vast current of life. In this respect there is no difference between workmen; 
the only difference is between the scale of what they have experienced and 
what they leave behind them."
   "But isn't it true that the name of such a man as Menni will not die with 
him, but will remain in the memory of humanity when the names of innu- 
merable others have disappeared without a trace?"
   "The name of every man is preserved so long as those are alive who 
knew him. But humanity does not need the dead symbol of a person when 
he is no more. Without regard for persons, our learning and our art pre- 
serve what has been accomplished by the commonality. The dead weight of 
names from the past is useless for humanity's tradition."
   "Perhaps you are right; but our feelings reject that logic. For us the 
names of thinkers and doers are living symbols essential for our learning, 
our art, and our social life. It often happens that in the struggle for ideas 
and accomplishments a name says more than an abstract slogan. And the 
names of geniuses are not a dead weight in our tradition."
  "That is because the common cause of humanity is still not yet a com- 
mon cause; thanks to the illusions which arise as the result of the struggle

 548        WORLDS APART
 among men, it is fragmented and appears to be a cause of men and 
humanity. It is as difficult for me to understand your point of view as 
for you to understand ours."
  `Then for better or for worse there are no immortals among the cre. 
But the mortals here are among the most select, isn't that so? From amore- 
those who have 'worked long and well,' as you expressed it?"
  "Yes, in general. Menni chose his comrades from thousands w 
wished to make the journey with him."
  "And next to him, isn't Sterni perhaps the most eminent?"
  "Yes, if you insist on measuring and comparing individuals. Sternys: 
remarkable scientist, although of a completely different sort than Menni..1-4 
is a very gifted mathematician. He discovered an entire set of errors in the 
calculations which were employed to send the former expeditions to Ea 
and he demonstrated that some of these errors were sufficient to destroYiiii. 
projects and their participants. He discovered new methods for making :.Su 
calculations and so far the results he obtained have been flawless."
  "I gathered this was so from Menni's words as well as from my o 
first impression. But still, and I don't understand this myself, I don't kno, 
why the sight of him makes me so uneasy, and arouses a kind of unfounded 
antipathy. Do you have any explanation for this, doctor?"
  "You see, Sterni has a great mind, but he is cold and above all, analYtio 
He dissects everything mercilessly and consistently but his conclusions 
often narrow and sometimes extremely harsh, because his analysis ofthe 
details is not unified, and is less than the whole: you know that always whO. 
there is life the whole is more than the sum of its parts, just as a living human 
body is more than an assemblage of its members. As a consequence, Stet* 
does not understand others' moods and ideas. He is always willing to he.p 
you with your problems but he can never understand what you need. In part 
this is the result of his preoccupation with his work; his mind is always bnSy 
with some difficult problem or other. In this respect he is very unlike Menrit..  
he always sees what is around him and sometimes he has been able to explain,- 
to me what I really want, or what is disturbing me, or what I long for."
  "If that's so, then isn't Sterni rather hostile to the inhabitants of Earth 
who are so full of contradictions and inadequacies?"
  "Hostile!—no; such a feeling is alien to him. But he is more skeptiCal 
than is necessary, I think. He lived in France for a half a year and wired 
Menni: 'Nothing here.' Perhaps he was partly right because Letta who 
with him was also unable to find anyone of interest. But the characteri* 
tions he gave to the people of that country whom he met were much harsher. 
than Letta's, and, of course, they were much more one-sided although there. 
was nothing in them which could be called inaccurate."
  "And who is this Letta you mentioned? I don't think I remember his name."

             Alexander Alexandrovich Bogdanov 549
   "A chemist, Menni's helper, not young, the oldest man on the space- 
 ship. You will find him very accessible and that will be useful to you. He is 
 gentle by nature and he understands others, although he is no psychologist 
 like Menni. Visit him in his laboratory; he will be pleased to see you and 
 can show you much that is interesting."
   It occurred to me that we were now far from the Earth, and I wanted 
 to look at her once more. We went to one of the accessory rooms equipped 
 with large windows.
   "Will we pass close to the moon?" I said as we walked along.
   "No, the moon will remain well out of our path, and I'm sorry that this 
 is so. I would like to see the moon up close. It seemed so strange to me from 
 Earth—large, cold, deliberate, mysteriously serene; it is so different from 
our two little moons which fly so swiftly through our sky, changing their 
faces so rapidly like living and capricious children. True, your moon is 
much brighter than ours and her light is so pleasant. Your sun is brighter, 
too; in this respect you are much more fortunate than we. Your world is 
twice as bright as ours and so you don't need eyes like ours with their great 
pupils to collect the weak light of our days and nights."
   We sat down at the window. Earth shone distantly below us like a giant 
sickle on which I could make out only the outlines of Western America, 
Northeastern Asia, a vague patch which was the Pacific Ocean and a white 
spot which was the Arctic. All of the Atlantic Ocean and the Old World lay 
in shadow; one could only surmise their existence beyond the uncertain 
edge of the sickle by the fact that the invisible part of Earth blotted out the 
stars over a great expanse of the black sky. Our curving trajectory and 
Earth's rotation on its axis led to this changing scene.
   I looked and I was sorry that I could not see my native land where there 
was so much life, so many struggles, so much pain, where yesterday I had 
stood in the ranks with my comrades and where another was now to take 
my place. And my heart was filled with doubts.
   "There, below us, blood is flowing," I said, and yesterday's worker is 
playing the role of a comfortable spectator . . ."
   "Blood is flowing for the sake of a better future," Netti answered, "and 
for the sake of the struggle you must come to know that better future. That 
is why you are here—to gain that knowledge."
   Involuntarily I pressed his little, almost childlike hand.

               CHAPTER VIII: THE APPROACH
   Earth was yet further now and, as though it were languishing, it was 
transformed into a crescent moon accompanied by another tiny crescent, 
the real moon. All of us, the inhabitants of the spaceship too were trans-

 550        WORLDS APART
 formed—into some kind of fantastic acrobats who could fly without wings , 
 and take any position in space, head to the floor or the ceiling or the walls, 
 almost indifferently ... Little by little I was coming to know my new com- 
 rades and to feel more at ease in their presence.
  On the second day after our departure (we continued to count the days, 
 although for us, of course, there were no real days and nights) on my own 
 initiative I dressed in Martian clothing, so I would not be so conspicuous 
 among the crew. True, I liked the costume for its own merits, since it was 
 comfortable without any useless, purely conventional features such as neck- 
 ties or cuffs and allowed maximum body movement. The individual parts 
 of the suit were connected by small ties so that the entire costume was one 
whole, but at the same rime, if it were necessary, it was simple to unfasten 
and remove, for example, one sleeve or both or the entire blouse. And the 
manners of my fellow-travelers were like their costume: simple and with an 
absence of anything that was superfluous or only decorative. They never 
greeted one another, nor said farewell, nor gave thanks, nor continued a 
conversation out of politeness if its end had been achieved; at the same time 
they patiently provided explanations which were painstakingly set at the 
level of the person with whom they were speaking and with understanding 
for his personality although it might very much differ from their own.
  Of course from the very first I turned to the study of their language and 
they all, and particularly Netti, willingly played the role of teachers. Their 
language was very unusual: in spite of the simplicity of its grammar and the 
rules for word formation, some of its features gave me great difficulties. The 
rules of its grammar had absolutely no exceptions and there was no such 
thing as a gender, masculine, feminine or neuter; but instead all the names 
of things and qualities were inflected in time. This I could not absorb.
  "What could be the purpose of such forms?" I asked Netti.
  "Don't you understand? In your languages you are very careful to indi- 
cate whether you consider a thing to be male or female, which is, you must 
admit, of no importance at all; and as far as inanimate objects are con- 
cerned, more than strange. It's much more important whether a thing exists 
at the present time or that it did at one time or will come into being. In your 
language "house" is masculine, but "boat" is feminine, but in French the 
reverse is true—but this has nothing to do with the state of things. When 
you talk about a house which has burned down or which is yet to be built, 
you employ the word in the same form as when you talk about the house 
in which you live. Isn't there actually much more of a difference between a 
man who is alive and a man who has died—between what is and what is 
no more? You need whole words and phrases to indicate this difference— 
wouldn't it be better to indicate it by adding one letter to the word itself?"
  But at any rate Netti was satisfied with my powers of memory and his

            Alexander Alexandrovich Bogdanov 551
 method of instruction was excellent and I made relatively rapid progress. 
 This helped me in my dealings with the Martians—now I could confident- 
 ly visit the entire spaceship, dropping into the rooms and laboratories of my 
 fellow travelers and asking about anything which interested me.
   The young astronomer, Enno, Sterni's aide, lively and cheerful, and still 
 a lad, explained many things to me, obviously carried away, not so much 
 by the measurements and formulas, of which he was a master, as by the 
 beauty of what he was observing. I was happy to be with the young 
 astronomer-poet; a very legitimate concern to orient myself in space gave 
 me a constant excuse to spend time with Enno and his telescopes.
   One time Enno in the greatest excitement showed me the tiny planet, 
 Eros, a segment of whose orbit passed between the paths of Earth and Mars 
 but which otherwise lay beyond Mars in the asteroid belt. Although at the 
 time Eros was located 100 million miles from us, a photograph of its tiny 
 crescent under the microscope was like a whole geographic chart, like the 
 maps of the moon. Of course it was also as lifeless as the moon.
   On another occasion, Enno photographed a flight of meteors which passed 
 several million miles from us. The picture showed, naturally, only an indefinite 
 haziness. At the time Enno told me that on one of the previous expeditions to 
 Earth a spaceship was destroyed when it passed through such a flight. 
 Astronomers who were following the spaceship in their telescopes saw how its 
 electric lights were extinguished—and the spaceship disappear in space forever.
   "The spaceship probably collided with several of these small bodies and 
 because of the great difference in speeds they must have passed right 
 through its walls. Then the air escaped out of it and the chill of interplane- 
 tary space froze the travelers. Now the spaceship is still flying, continuing 
 its journey in a comet's orbit; it has left the sun forever and no one knows 
 where it will end, a terrible craft manned by corpses."
   As Enno spoke I could feel the cold of empty space invade my heart. I 
 imagined our minute, glowing island in the midst of an endless dead sea, 
 without any support moving at a dizzying pace with only a black void 
 around us ... Enno guessed how I felt.
   "Menni is an excellent navigator," he said, "and Sterni makes no mis- 
 takes . . . And death . . . You've seen it before during your life . . . Death is 
 death, nothing more." Soon the time would come when I would remember 
 those words in my struggle with a great spiritual sickness.
   I was attracted to the chemist Letta nor only because of his extraordinary 
 gentleness and sensitivity, which Netti had told me about, but also because of 
 his enormous knowledge of the field which interested me more than any 
other—the nature of matter. Only Menni was better informed on this ques- 
tion, but I tried to have as little as possible to do with him, knowing that his 
time was too valuable both for science and for the interests of the expedition,

552         WORLDS APART
so that I had no right to distract him for my own purposes. But Letta, a 
old man, was so endlessly patient with my ignorance and so help 
explained to me the basic facts of the subject, even betraying pleasure wh 
he did so, that I always felt quite unconstrained in his presence.
 Letta began to deliver a whole series of lectures to me on the theory 
matter, illustrating them with a number of experiments on the decompositiO 
and synthesis of the elements. He had to omit a number of the relevant exile 
invents-limiting himself to a description of them—which were violent in nap 
and were accompanied by an explosion or which might take that form.
 During one of these lectures Menni entered the laboratory. Letta w 
finishing the description of a very interesting experiment and was about 
begin its execution.
 "Be careful," Menni told him, "I remember once when I performed 
it came to a bad end; only a trace of impurities in the substance which y 
are decomposing and even a weak electrical spark is enough to cause 
explosion when you are heating it."
 Lena wanted to abandon the experiment, but Menni, who was invariably 
thoughtful and considerate in his relations with me, offered to help him check 
the elements of the experiment; the reaction occurred without difficulty.
 The next day there were to be more experiments with the same sub 
stance. It seemed to me that Lena did not take his materials out of the sail 
container as the previous day. When he placed the retort in the electric fur 
nace it occurred to me to say something to him. Disturbed, he immediately 
went to the locker where the reagents were stored, leaving the furnace and 
the retort on the table near the wall which was also the outer wall of the 
spaceship. I went with him.
 Suddenly there was a deafening roar and both of us were blown against 
the locker with great force. This was followed by a deafening whistle and 
howling and the sound of breaking metal. I felt an irresistible force, like a hur- 
ricane, pulling me back toward the outer wall. I had time to seize a firmly 
attached strap on the locker and hung horizontally, held in that position by a 
powerful stream of air. Lena did the same thing.
 "Hold on!" he shouted and I could hardly hear his voice in the midst 
of the storm.
 Letta quickly looked around. His face was terribly pale, but the appear- 
ance of indecisiveness was replaced by one expressing thought and firm 
decision. He said only two words—I couldn't make them out, but it seemed 
that he was saying farewell forever-and his hands relaxed their grip.
 There was a dull blow and the hurricane ceased. I felt I could release 
my hold and looked around. The table was completely gone and against the 
wall, his spine flat against the wall, stood Letta. His eyes were open wide 
and his face seemingly frozen. In one leap I reached the door and opened it.

            Alexander Alexandravich Bogdanov 553
A stream of warm air threw me back. Menni entered the room in a second 
and quickly went up to Letta.
   A few seconds later the room was full. Netti entered, pushing everyone 
to the side and rushed to Letta. All the rest of us surrounded them in painful 
silence.
   "Letta is dead," Menni said. "The explosion which occurred during the 
experiment punctured the spaceship's wall and Letta closed the aperture 
with his own body. The air pressure ruptured his lungs and paralyzed his 
heart—it was a quick death. Letta saved our guest's life—otherwise they 
would both have died."
   Netti suddenly burst into tears.

   CHAPTER IX. THE PAST—[The chapter consists of an unambiguous 
rehashing of history from a dialectic point of view—shown to be equally 
applicable to Mars and to Earth—which supposedly led the much older 
Martian society to a classless paradise after the building of its canals. A. L.J.

                 CHAPTER X. ARRIVAL
   Under Menni's cool hand the spaceship made its way without further 
mishaps toward its distant destination. I had become tolerably accustomed 
to conditions of weightlessness and I had mastered the majpr difficulties of 
the Martian language when Menni announced that we had completed half 
of our journey and had achieved our maximum speed, henceforth to decline.
   At a time carefully determined by Menni, the spaceship swiftly and 
smoothly reversed itself. The Earth, which had been a great and brilliant 
sickle, then a smaller one, and then a greenish star close to a sun's disk, now 
left the lower half of the black sky and entered the upper half, while the red 
star of Mars which had shown bright above our heads was now below us.
  After many days had passed, the star of Mars became a clear small disc 
with its two stars, its satellites, Deimos and Phobos, innocent, miniscule, 
undeserving of their threatening Greek names "Horror" and "Terror." The 
Martians were now elated and frequently visited Enno's observatory to 
view their native land. I too observed it but found it difficult to understand 
that I saw in spite of Enno's patient explanations. There was much there, in 
fact, which was strange to me.
  The red spots were forests and meadows while the dark places were 
fields ready for the harvest. The cities were bluish patches—only water and 
snow had their familiar hues. The ebullient Enno sometimes asked me to 
identify what I saw in the eye-piece and my innocent misinterpretations 
vastly amused him and Netti; I in turn repaid them for their jokes, calling 
their planet a kingdom of learned owls and confused colors.

          WORLDS APART
 The dimensions of the red disk were constantly increasing—now it w 
much larger than the noticeably diminishing sun and it looked like an astr  
nomical chart without labels. The force of gravity also was increasm 
which was surprisingly pleasant to me. From bright specks of light Deimo 
and Phobos were transfoemed into tiny, but well-defined circles.
 Fifteen or twenty hours later Mars, like a flattened ball, opened 04 
below us and with the naked eye I could see more than was shown on all 
our scientists' astronomical charts. Deimos glided over that round map, but 
Phobos was nowhere to be seen—it was on the other side of the planet.
 Everyone around me was rejoicing; only I was beset by uneasy foreboding'
 Closer and closer . . . No one could work any longer—they all we 
watching the ground below us, a different world, their native land, but for 
me a place of mystery and the unknown. Only Menni was absent—he was:; 
at the engine; the last hours of the journey were the most dangerous time 
and he had to regulate the craft's speed and verify its distance from Mars
 And what was the matter with me, the involuntary Columbus of t 
world, why did I feel no joy, no pride, nor even the peace of mind whic 
dry land should have brought me after journey across the seas of the' 
Unknown? Future events had already cast their shadow over the present..
 Only two hours remained and soon we would enter the planet's atmos- 
phere. My heart began to pound; I could not watch any longer and I went 
to my room. Netti followed me.
 He began to talk to me, not about the present, but the past, and the dis=  
tant Earth high above us.
 "You will have to return there after you have completed your assign.- 
ment," he said, and his words were a gentle reminder of my own courage:
 We talked about assignement, its importance and its problems. Time 
passed for me unnoticed.
 Netti looked at the chronometer. "We are there, let's go to my people!" 
he said.
 The spaceship stopped, broad metal doors opened and fresh air 
streamed in. Over our heads was a clean greenish-blue sky and around us 
were crowds of people.
 Menni and Sterni were the first to leave, carrying in their arms a trans-  
parent coffin where lay the frozen body of Letta, their dead comrade.
 The others followed after them. Netti and I were the last to leave and 
hand in hand we made our way through the throngs of people all of whom 
looked like him...
 [End of Part I]
                 Translated by Leland Fetzer

