                     NIKOLAI F. FYODOROV
                                 1892















              KARAZIN: 
   METEOROLOGIST OR METEORURGE?
 In this essay we will talk about Karazin, a man of many talents, 
not as a meteorologist but as a meteor-urge. The difference between 
a meteorologist and a meteorurge may be defined as follows: the 
ultimate objective of the first is to predict famine, and the second takes 
as his task — and incidentally, only as the first step of the task — salvation 
from famine. Unfortunately, the word urge was corrupted by mystics 
and acquired the connotation of witchcraft — arcane, supernatural acts, 
unseen influences of spirits — and not the clear, open, comprehensive 
exercise of reason on the blind forces of nature.
 While attempting to manufacture saltpeter, an idea occurred to 
Karazin: potassium nitrate could be made with electricity captured 
from the atmosphere's highest strata by specially constructed balloons, 
which would be anchored to the earth with metallic cables. On the 
9th of April, 1814, Karazin wrote about this to Arakcheyev, residing 
in Paris at that time. Among other matters, he mentioned: "If the

32           Red Star Tales

experiment, as I hope, conclusively confirms my hypothesis about 
extracting electricity from the stratosphere, it will signal the invention 
of a new, unprecedented weapon in the hands of humankind. Water, air, 
fire, muscles of living beings, tension, and expansion of certain bodies 
are still considered to be regulated by natural forces, some of which 
we have managed to harness and replicate in machines. Consider, 
your excellency, the consequences of mastering the massive amount 
of electrical energy scattered throughout the atmosphere and bending 
it to our will." Subsequently Karazin expresses hope that through the 
medium of electricity, humans "will attain the ability to determine the 
state of the atmosphere, producing rain at will." Intrigued, "Arakcheyev 
showed Karazin's letter to the renowned chemist Chaptal, an expert in 
the production of saltpeter, who unconditionally approved its contents." 
This opinion was echoed by the committee that Prince Gorchakov, 
head of the Ministry of Defense, appointed in 1815 in order to review 
Karazin's proposal of creating condensed explosives and saltpeter 
for military purposes. Professor Scherer, a chemist and member of 
the Imperial Academy of Sciences, responded to the committee that 
"according to his own observations, which he intended to publish, he 
saw no other explanation for the creation of potassium nitrate, even in 
the usual course of producing saltpeter, than the effect of atmospheric 
electricity. Finally, Karazin managed to get the attention of His 
Majesty Alexander Pavlovich himself, to whom Karazin conveyed 
a note about meteorology during the latter's tour through Kharkov 
in September 1817. His Royal Highness was particularly taken by 
the following words in the note: "The implementation of electricity 
from higher atmospheric strata for the benefit of humankind. The 
important invention presented herewith could be applied only at a 
small scale due to the inadequacy of resources. It accords with our 
age and Russia's glorious position within it. As a patriot, it would be 
a pity for me to see a foreigner stumble upon this very same idea." 
In response to the sovereign's request for further elaboration, Karazin 
submitted a new document in which he proposed — based on the 
fact that the higher one ascends in the atmosphere, the higher the

          Karazin: Meteorologist or Meteorurge?  33

concentration of electricity — that the highest strata of the atmosphere 
"consist of a perpetual upheaval, like a sea in stormy weather, from 
the arriving and departing oscillations of electric currents.... Why is 
it impossible to think that humanity can tame electric power as it has 
tamed animals, water, wind, and fire? It all depends on reaching the 
source of the power and creating a channel for directing it for this 
or that purpose, according to our will. But the source in this case is 
the farthest height of the atmosphere; metallic cables may serve as the 
channels, and balloons as anchors for holding down the ends of the 
cables at a constant height." Recalling the salient chemical properties 
of electricity, Karazin warns that "the largest electric machine, clad in 
strips of metal foil and sailing through the heights of the atmosphere, 
will be a child's toy vis-à-vis a mid-sized zeppelin, comparable with a 
miniature model sailboat set against an English battleship on its course. 
Man in all his ingenuousness can never replicate the immeasurable scale 
of nature. He can only hope to discover the best ways to implement 
her resources." That is to say, humanity is not meant to compete 
with nature, but only to regulate her. "Experiments conducted with 
the proposed equipment will undoubtedly be astounding. The results 
may include the following. 1) The most accurate information about 
the factors of changing atmospheric conditions. This data, combined 
with general meteorological observations, would open the way for 
transforming meteorology into an exact science, i.e., a science as 
capable of calculating and predicting the weather in given places at 
given times as astronomy is accurate in predicting eclipses.... Our 
country has a distinct advantage in realizing this vision.... No other 
kingdom is endowed with such breadth and variety of landscapes for 
conducting such experiments as our Russia. 2) The achievements 
of chemistry and technology... In the north, manufacturing and 
industry will be powered naturally by harnessing the sun's energy. 3) 
Benefits of land management." This proposal was forwarded to the 
academy of sciences, where Nikolai Fuss interpreted its contents at 
the members' conference. Fuss concluded that quite a few methods 
already existed for harnessing electricity in amounts sufficient "for

34            Red Star Tales

fulfilling all technical demands," and that "most, if not all, of Karazin's 
supposed predictions were nothing more than hypotheses without any 
proof." Therefore the 20,000 rubles Karazin had deemed necessary for 
conducting his experiments "would be spent in vain," Fuss concluded. 
Although precisely this conclusion was marked by an anonymous 
penciled comment — "Russia won't go very far on Fusses like these" 
 — nevertheless Fuss' opinion prevailed, and Karazin's project, which 
 would have provided humanity with real power to eradicate suffering, 
 remained untested. Incidentally, "a project for manufacturing an acid 
 to power Leppikh's zeppelin, capable of carrying enough passengers 
 and explosives to blow up all the fortifications or personnel of the 
 greatest military powers" was awarded 40,000 rubles.
  Thus "the representatives of Russian science conclusively rejected 
 the Karazin proposal; they did not notice what was original and 
 productive about it." It is worth noting that Karazin's thoughts stood 
 so far out of the mainstream that they may even be inaccessible to our 
 contemporaries. Theories and projects pertaining to Karazin's areas 
 of interest are viewed suspiciously by, and elicit scant response from, 
 the worldly trade and industrial sectors that hold the public captive 
 and condition it to such an extent that people cannot conceive of a 
 common task to rally around; they are in fact repelled by any task that 
 requires collective effort; after all, Karazin's plans would have required 
 exactly such a collective effort involving everyone, all of humanity 
 from all walks of life.
  Considering that the military has recently begun to incorporate 
 aircraft, it would be easy to attach the equipment proposed by 
 Karazin to the existing infrastructure to carry out experiments. But 
 I doubt if we will have the patience to await the results; in order to 
 eliminate errors and arrive at the correct conclusions in projects such 
 as Karazin's, it is first necessary to apprehend the genuine importance 
 of its subject matter. Alas, in Karazin's own words, "the relevance of 
 the subject may not be fully comprehensible to ordinary citizens and 
 bevies of magazine critics," i.e. neither to those who are expected 
 to make reasonable judgments nor to those who, living in cities and

          Karaz n: Meteorologist or Meteorurge? 35

captives in the rhythms of urban life, have lost the ability to understand 
the meaning of the interdependence between sentient beings and the blind, 
unfeeling forces of- nature. And this interdependence — which we are 
compelled to acknowledge as unavoidable, preordained, superseding 
all the achievements and vanities of modern man — is the primal 
riddle that humanity, whether consciously or unconsciously, has been 
attempting to solve. In antiquity, the awareness of the meaning of 
this interdependence was encoded in the myth of the Sphinx, which 
asked passers-by to solve riddles; the wrong answer would cost the 
human interlocutor his life, while the Sphinx would die if the riddle 
was solved. As the whole of humankind is about to face the Sphinx, 
it is consequently obliged to work towards a solution to the riddle, 
i.e. to marshal all its current resources and seek additional ones in 
order to resolve its differences with the blind, intractable forces of 
nature that herald nothing but death in all its different manifestations. 
Intractable nature, precisely because it is intractable, is an agent of 
death; ignorance is the gravest sin, punishable by death. However, 
as darkness and gloom melt away before light, this blind force will 
disappear when light floods each and every human life emerging on 
earth — instead of remaining limited to a small minority, where it 
loses its innate properties and appears as a mere gleam. As long as 
one social group commands some knowledge without possessing 
any power, and the other wields some power but remains largely 
ignorant, the knowledge of the former will not be genuinely capable of 
regulating power, while the blind actions of the latter will necessarily 
be ineffective and repetitive despite all humankind's pride at possessing 
so-called cognition, which hardly deserves its name. A spark from the 
electrical generator may have all the properties of a lightning bolt, its 
crackle may possess the characteristics of thunder, but producing this 
tiny discharge does not make us Jupiters or free us from that deity's 
power. Even Karazin's brand of redirecting thunder, when it becomes 
ubiquitous and is carried out according to plan, will only be a step, the 
first step, towards the regulation of blind meteorological processes of 
the planet.

36           Red Star Tales

 Humanity is faced with two choices. Acknowledge that life is 
evil and aim towards self-destruction (Buddhism), or, if life is good, 
then within this acknowledgment lies the motivation for restoring 
it, which is exactly the same as the Christian tenet of resurrection; 
surely the goal of transforming the blind forces of famine, plague, 
and death into life-affirming ones should unite all of us. To consider 
destruction good (as Count L. N. Tolstoy preaches) is the same as 
believing that there is no good; it is equivalent to Buddhism, which 
considers life evil; this means renouncing Christianity, which only 
the most ignorant would confuse with Buddhism.
 The very forces of nature ask to be regulated by humans, and 
show them where to begin this task. As long as maritime powers, 
originating in countries with temperate climates and nurturing skies, 
dominated world history, the question of regulating meteorological 
phenomena could remain on the margins; but from the moment 
when land-based powers with extreme climates that fluctuate 
suddenly between drought and cloudbursts entered the scene, this 
question began to demand a solution. And if in Russia it had not 
emerged at the center of attention until now, this was only because 
we lived under the epistemological yoke of countries for which it 
was not urgent. Moreover, the solution demands methods and 
approaches that are not available to our role models. It is necessary 
to change the very foundations of producing knowledge and make 
the new paradigms universal, omnipresent, and eternal, to unify all 
experimental knowledge into one. Fortunately, while blind nature, 
afraid of its own extinction, begs for the unification of all rational 
forces — and rational forces, armed with weapons of mass destruction, 
unwillingly consider both the imperative of disarmament and its 
impossibility — the opportunity arises to remake the greatest evil into 
the greatest good. People who can band together to fight in the army, 
i.e., as a unified mass according to a given plan, can easily fulfill the 
primary criteria of a great common task: ubiquity and universality. 
The only remaining step is to bring meteorological observations 
into the sphere of peaceable military exercises, to test not only the

           Karazin: Meteorologist or Meteorurge? 37

American method of creating rain with explosives, but also Karazin's 
project, and all the other ways of acting on nature that will emerge as 
soon as they receive the close, intensive attention long due to them.

                                 First published in Russian: 1892 
                                 Translation by Anindita Banerjee

