                          KONSTANTIN TSIOLKOVSKY1893,














                  ON THE MOON

  I woke up and, still lying in bed, pondered the dream I'd just ha 
I was swimming, and since it's winter now it felt especially pleasant 
imagine summer swimming.
  Time to get up!
  I stretched, lifted myself up a bit... So easy! It was easy to sit, easy; 
stand. What was going on? Could I still be dreaming? I felt especi 
light, as if I were standing in water up to my neck: my feet bare 
touched the floor.
  But where was the water? I didn't see any. I waved my hands, an 
sensed no resistance.
  Was I still asleep? I rubbed my eyes, but everything stayed the s 
  Strange!
  Nonetheless, I had to get dressed.
  I moved the chairs, opened the cupboards, got out my cloth' 
picked up various things, and — nothing made any sense!

            On the Moon        39

 aye I gotten stronger? Why is everything so weightless? Why 
  pick up objects I couldn't even budge before?
  These were not my legs, not my arms, not my body!
 wally they were so heavy, and everything took them so much

  ere had I acquired such might in my arms and legs?
  maybe some kind of power was pulling me and everything else 
ward, and making my work easier that way? But if so, what a strong 
  st a little more, it seemed to me, and I'd float up to the ceiling. 
  y was it I leapt instead of walking? Something was pulling me 
  opposite direction to gravity; it tensed my muscles, forced me 
   jump.
   dn't resist the temptation — I jumped...
 seemed that I rose up fairly slowly and landed just as slowly.
   ped harder and took a look around the room from a fair 
  ice up... Ouch! Hit my head on the ceiling... The rooms are 
  `hadn't expected to hit it. I'd have to be more careful.
  'shout woke up my roommate, though: I saw him start tossing
    g, and after a little while he jumped out of bed. I won't 
   his amazement, just like my own. I observed the same kind 
   de I had acted out myself, without noticing it, a few minutes 
   t gave me great pleasure to see my friend's eyes bugging out, 
   y poses and the unnatural liveliness of his movements. His 
   exclamations, very like my own, amused me.
  aited for my friend the physicist to recover from his surprise, 
  asked Whim to resolve my question: what on earth had happened 
    strength increased, or did our weight decrease?
   suggestions were equally astounding, but there's nothing a 
  n won't start to view with indifference once he gets used to it. My 
   d I hadn't gotten that far yet, but we already felt a desire to 
   t the answer.
   end, who was accustomed to analysis, soon made sense of the 
   henotnena that had overwhelmed and confused my mind.

      40             Red Star Tales


        "We can test our muscle strength on the dynamometer, with the 
      spring weights," he said, "and find out whether it has increased or not. 
      Here, I'll press my feet against the wall and pull on the lower hook of 
      the spring. See — five poods:' my strength hasn't increased. You can do 
      the same, and prove to yourself that you haven't turned into a fairy-tale 
      hero like Ilya Muromets."
        "It's hard to agree," I objected. "The facts contradict you. How is it 
      that I can lift the edge of this bookcase, which has to weigh at least fifty 
      poods? At first I thought it must be empty, but I opened it and saw that 
      every book was still in place... Can you explain, by the way, how it is 
      that I can jump twenty arshins high!?"2
        "You aren't lifting heavy weights, jumping high and feeling light 
      because your own strength increased — we've already disproved that 
      hypothesis with the dynamometer — but because gravity is lower, and 
      you can prove that to yourself with the same spring weights. We can 
      even find out how much lower it is..."
        With these words he lifted the first weight he found, a twelve- 
      pounder, and hung it on the dynamometer.
        "Looks" he continued, pointing at the scale. "A twelve-pound weight 
      turns out to weigh two pounds. That means gravity has weakened by 
      a factor of six."
        After thinking for a minute, he continued, "That's just the gravity 
      on the surface of the Moon, due to its small volume and the low density 
      of its composition."
        "So are we on the Moon now?" I laughed.
        "If we are on the Moon," the physicist laughed, in the same joking 
       tone, "that's not a huge misfortune, since we can repeat a miracle like 
       that, given that it's possible, in the opposite direction — that is, we'll be 
       able to go back where we came from."
        "Wait, enough playing games... But what if we weigh something 
       on an ordinary cross-beam scale! Will we see a reduction in weight?"



       1. Rood - a pre-Revolutionary Russian measure, approximately 16.4 kilograms to one good.      2. arshin - a pre-Revolutionary Russian measure, approximately 71 centimeters.
.      2. arshin - a pre-Revolutionary Russian measure, approximately 71 centimeters.

On the Moon	
41
"No, because the weight of the thing will be reduced by the same  
amount as the weight you put in the other cup of the scales, since  
balance is not violated, regardless of the decrease in gravity."
"Yes, I see."
Nevertheless I still tried to snap a stick, hoping to discover an  
increase in my strength. I didn't succeed, by the way, though the stick  
wasn't thick and I had already bent it yesterday.
. "You're so stubborn! Give it up!" said my friend the physicist.  

"Instead, think about how the whole world must be disturbed by these  
changes..."
"You're right," 1 said, throwing down the stick. "I had forgotten  
about everything. 1 forgot about the existence of humanity, with which  
.1 feel a passionate desire to share my thoughts, just as you do..."
"Has anything happened to our friends? Have there been any other  
major changes?"
1 opened my mouth and yanked aside the curtain (they were all
•	
drawn at night to block the moonlight that kept us from sleeping), to
•.exchange a few words with our neighbor, but I jumped back on the  
double. Oh horror! el'he sky was blacker than the blackest ink!  
Where was the city? Where were all the people?
.	
•
It was some kind of wild, unimaginable, brightly sunlit place!
•	
Could we really have been taken away to some desert planet?  
•
All that stayed in my thoughts. I couldn't say anything, I just mooed  
something incoherently.
. My friend was about to rush over to me, thinking that I must be  

sick, but I gestured towards the window. He leaned to look out and  
so fell silent.
•	
If we didn't fall down in a faint, it was only thanks to the low gravity,  
which kept too much blood from flowing to our hearts.
We looked at each other.
•The curtains on the windows were still drawn; the thing that had  
struck us wasn't visible to our eyes. The ordinary look of the room and  
the familiar things in it calmed us down even more.

42           Red Star Tales

 We drew together with a certain timidity and lifted only the edge 
of the little curtain first, then lifted the whole thing and then, finally, 
made up our minds to go out of the house to observe the sky, black as 
mourning, and our surroundings.
 Even though our thoughts were preoccupied by the stroll we 
were about to take, we were still noticing certain things. So, as we 
walked through the spacious and high-ceilinged rooms, we had to 
move our large muscles with extreme care, otherwise our soles would 
slide uselessly on the floor — without the risk of falling, however, the 
way there is on wet snow or on frozen ground. When we did this our 
bodies jumped noticeably. When we wanted to put ourselves into rapid 
horizontal motion, to start moving we had to lean forward noticeably, 
the way a horse leans to pull an overloaded wagon. But it only seemed 
that way — in fact all our movements were extremely light... Going 
downstairs from one step to the next — how boring! Moving step by 
step — how slow! Soon we got rid of all those ceremonious habits, 
which suited the Earth but were ridiculous here. We learned to move 
by leaping; we started going up and down stairs ten or more at a time, 
like the most reckless schoolboys; or sometimes we'd jump the whole 
length of the staircase or right out the window. In a word, circumstances 
forced us to turn into leaping animals like grasshoppers or frogs.
 Thus, after running around the house a bit, we jumped outside and 
galloped off towards one of the nearest mountains.
 The Sun was blinding and looked a bit bluish. Shading our eyes 
with our hands against the Sun and the brilliant reflected light from 
the surroundings, we could see the stars and planets, also for the most 
part bluish. None of them were twinkling, which made them look like 
silver-headed nails hammered into the black firmament.
 Ah, and there was the Moon — in its last quarter! Well, it couldn't 
fail to surprise us, since its width seemed three or four times greater 
than the diameter of the Moon we had seen before. And it shone 
brighter than by day on Earth, when the Moon shows up like a white 
puff of cloud. Silence... clear weather... a cloudless sky... There were 
no plants and no animals.. A desert with a black sky and a blue, dead

              On the Moon         43

Sun. No lake, no stream, and not a drop of water! Even the horizon 
wasn't any paler — that would have indicated the presence of vapors, 
but it was just as dark as the zenith!
  There was none of the wind that rustles the grass and tosses the tops 
 of the trees on Earth... There was no chirping of crickets... No sign of 
 any birds, or colorful butterflies! Just mountains and more mountains, 
 horrible, high mountains, whose peaks didn't gleam with snow. Not 
 a flake of snow anywhere! There were the valleys, plains, plateaus... 
 How many rocks were scattered there... Black and white, large and 
 small, but all sharp, shining, not rounded, not softened by a wave, since 
 no sea ever rolled here, ever played with them with a cheerful sound, 
 ever labored over them!
  But there was a completely smooth place, though rippled: you 
 couldn't see a single pebble, only black cracks crawling in all directions, 
 like snakes... Hard ground — stony... No soft black soil: no sand and 
 no clay.
  A gloomy picture! Even the mountains were bare, shamelessly 
 unclothed, since we didn't see the light veil, the transparent bluish 
 smoke that the air casts over earthly mountains and distant objects... 
 Severe, strikingly precise landscapes! And the shadows! Oh, what 
 dark shadows! And what sharp transitions from shade to light! There 
 were none of the soft tones that we're so used to and that can be 
 produced only by an atmosphere. Even the Sahara — even that would 
 seem a paradise in comparison with what we saw here. We missed 
 its scorpions, the locusts, the hot sand lifted by the dry wind, not to 
 mention the occasional sparse vegetation and groves of fig trees... We 
 had to think about returning. The ground was cold and exuded cold, 
 so that our feet were chilling, while the Sun baked us. Overall, we felt 
 an unpleasant sensation of cold. It was like when a person comes in 
 from the cold to warm up in front of a blazing fireplace and can't get 
 warm, because it too cold in the room: his skin feels pleasant waves of 
 warmth that can't overcome the chill.

44           Red Star Tales

  On the way back we warmed ourselves by leaping as lightly as deer 
over piles of stones two sazhens high...3 There was granite, porphyry, 
syenite, quartz crystals and various pieces of transparent and opaque 
quartz and flint, all of igneous origin. Later, though, we noticed traces 
of neptunic activity.
  We were back in the house!
  Inside you feel good: the temperature's more even. That put us in 
the mood to start trying new experiments and to discuss everything 
we had seen and noticed. Clearly, we were on some other planet. This 
planet had no air, nor any other kind of atmosphere.
  If there had been gas, then the stars would have twinkled; if there 
had been air, the sky would have been blue and there would have been 
a blue veil on the distant mountains. But how was it that we could 
breathe and hear each other? We couldn't understand it. A multitude 
of phenomena made it clear to us that there was no air or any kind of 
gas at all: for example, we couldn't light a cigar and in our haste we 
spoiled a lot of matches. We could also compress a sealed rubber bag 
without the slightest force, which wouldn't have been the case if there 
had been any kind of gas inside it. Scientists have indicated this lack of 
gasses on the Moon.
  "Could it be that we're on the Moon?"
  "Have you noticed that from here the Sun doesn't seem any bigger 
or any smaller than from the Earth? Such a phenomenon can be 
observed only from the Earth or from its satellite, since these heavenly 
bodies are located almost the same distance from the Sun. From other 
planets the Sun must appear either smaller or larger: so, from Jupiter 
the visible diameter of the Sun is five times smaller, and from Mars, 
one and a half times smaller, but from Venus, on the other hand, one 
and a half times greater. On Venus the Sun burns twice as brightly, 
but on Mars, only half as brightly. And that's just the difference from 
the two planets closest to the Earth! On Jupiter, for example, the Sun 
gives twenty-five times less heat than on the Earth. We see nothing

3. sazhen -- a pre-Revolunonary Russian measure, approximately 2.13 meters.

             On the Moon        45

ke that difference here, even though measuring it would be entirely 
possible thanks to the store of instruments for measuring carbon and 
other things."
 "Yes, we're on the Moon: everything points to that!"
 "Even the size of the clouded moon we saw suggests that — it's 
obviously the planet we left, not of our own volition. Too bad we can't 
examine its spots now and definitively define our own location. We'll 
wait for night time..."
 "How can you say that Earth and the Moon are at the same distance 
from the Sun?" I objected to my friend. "I thought the difference was 
quite significant! Why, as far as I know, they are three hundred sixty 
thousand versts apart!"
 "I'm saying they're almost at the same distance, since those three 
hundred sixty thousand versts comprise only one four-hundredth 
of the entire distance to the Sun," objected the physicist. "A four- 
hundredth can be disregarded."

                 II
 How tired I was, and not so much physically as mentally! I felt 
irresistibly drawn to sleep... What did the clock say? We got up at six, 
now it was five... eleven hours had passed. At the same time, judging 
by the shadows, the Sun had hardly moved: there the shadow from the 
steep mountain had barely moved towards the house, and even now it 
didn't quite reach, while over there the shadow from the weathervane 
was still touching the same stone...
 This was one more proof that we were on the Moon.
 In fact, its rotation around its axis is so slow... Here a day should 
last around fifteen of our days, or three hundred and sixty hours, and a 
night should last just as long. It's not entirely comfortable... The sun 
would interfere with your sleep! I remember, I experienced the same 
thing when I had to live several weeks in the summer in polar countries: 
the Sun never set on the horizon, and it got really tiresome! Here the 
Sun moves slowly, but in the same order; there it moves quickly, and 
every twenty-four hours it makes a circle low above the horizon...

46          Red Star Tales

 Here and there you could use one and the same solution: close the 
shutters.
 But was the clock right? Why was there such a disagreement 
between my wristwatch and the clock on the wall? My wristwatch said 
five, but the one on the wall showed just ten... Which one was right? 
Why was the wall clock's pendulum swinging so lazily?
 Obviously, that clock was slow!
 My wristwatch couldn't be wrong, since it didn't have a pendulum 
swung by weight, but the tension of a steel spring, which was the same 
on the Moon as it was on Earth.
 You could check that by measuring your pulse. Mine was seventy 
beats per minute... Now it was seventy-five. A bit faster, but that could 
be due to the nervous excitement from the unusual setting and strong 
impressions.
 Anyway, there was still one more way to check the time: at night we 
would see the Earth, which turns once every twenty-four hours. That's 
the best, the least erroneous clock!
  Regardless of the sleepiness that had overcome both of us, my 
physicist couldn't bear not to fix the wall clock. I saw him lifting the  
long pendulum, measuring it exactly and shortening it to one sixth 
or thereabouts. The honorable clock turned into a little tick-tack. 
But here it wasn't a tick-tack, for the shortened pendulum behaved 
gravely, though not so gravely as the long one had. Thanks to this 
metamorphosis the wall clock started to agree with my wristwatch.
  At last we went to bed and covered up with our light blankets, which 
seemed weightless here.
  We hardly needed to use our pillows and mattresses. Here, it 
seemed, you could sleep even on bare boards.
  I couldn't get rid of the thought that it was still too early to go to  
bed. Oh, this Sun! This time! You were both standing still, like all time 
on the Moon!
  My comrade stopped answering me, and I fell asleep too.
  A jolly waking... cheerfulness and a wolf's appetite... Until now our 
excitement had displaced our usual appetite.

              On the Moon         47

  I was thirsty! I pulled out the cork... But what's this — the water was 
boiling! Only slightly, but it was boiling. I touched the decanter with 
my hand. I didn't want to burn myself... No, the water was merely 
warm. It was unpleasant to drink water like that!
  "What do you say, my physicist?"
  "There's a complete vacuum here, that's why the water's boiling, 
it's not prevented by the pressure of Earth's atmosphere. Let it boil 
a bit more: don't close the stopper! In a vacuum boiling ends up by 
freezing....But we won't let it get to freezing... That's enough! Pour 
some water in the glass, and put the stopper in, otherwise a lot will 
boil away."
  Liquid poured slowly on the Moon!
  The water calmed down in the decanter, but in the glass it continued 
its lifeless boiling though the longer it went on, the more weakly.
  The water left in the glass turned into ice, but the ice still evaporated 
and shrank in mass.
  Flow would we have lunch now?
  We could eat the bread and other more or less solid food freely, 
though it quickly dried up in a box that wasn't hermetically sealed: the 
bread turned into rock, the fruits shrank and also got pretty hard. On 
the other hand, their skins still retained some moisture.
  "Oh, this habit of eating something hot! How can we manage it? 
You can't make a fire here: there's no wood, no coal, even the matches 
don't burn!"
  "Can't we use the Sun for this? You know, they bake eggs in the hot 
sand of the Sahara!"
  WC fixed our pots and pans and other vessels so that their lids 
closed tightly and firmly. We filled everything with what was needed, 
according to the rules of the culinary arts, and put it all in a pile in the 
sun. Then we gathered all the mirrors in the house and set them up so 
they reflected the Sun's light onto the pots and pans.
  Before even an hour had passed, we could dine on foods that were 
well boiled and fried.

48               Red Star Tales


  And what can I say! Have you heard of Mouchot?4 His perfected 
 solar delicacies were far behind ours! Boasting and bragging? Call 
 it that if you like... You can blame these self-satisfied words on our 
 ravenous appetites, which would have made any kind of vile stuff seem 
 delightful.
   Only one thing was bad: we had to hurry. I admit it, we stuffed 
 ourselves and choked. You'll understand this if I say that the soup 
 boiled and got cold not only in the bowls, but even in our mouths, 
 our throats and digestive tracts; the moment we got distracted — look, 
 instead of soup there was a lump of ice...
   Its a wonder our digestive systems stayed in one piece! The pressure 
 of the steam stretched them out a great deal...
   In any case, we were satisfied and fairly calm. We didn't understand 
 how it was we could live without air, and how it was we ourselves, our 
 house, garden, and the stores of food and drink in the pantries and 
 cellars had been transferred from Earth to the Moon. We were even 
 struck by doubt, and we thought: isn't this a dream, a daydream or a 
 demonic delusion? And along with all that we got used to our situation 
 and related to it partly with curiosity, partly with indifference: what we 
 couldn't explain didn't surprise us, and the danger of dying of hunger, 
 alone and miserable, didn't even enter our minds.
   You'll learn the reason for our impossible optimism at the end of 
 our adventures.
   We wanted to take a stroll after eating... I didn't dare sleep a lot: I 
 was afraid of suffering a stroke.
   I distracted my friend, too.
   We were in a spacious yard, with gymnastics equipment in its center, 
 and on its sides a fence and outbuildings.
   Why was this rock here? A person could trip and fall on it. In the 
 yard the ground was ordinary earthly soil, soft. Out with it, over the 
 fence! Be confident! Don't be frightened by the size! And there we 
 lifted a stone of sixty poods by our mutual efforts and tossed it over


 4. Augustin Mouchot (1825-1911), French inventor of a boiler that used solar power to heat water 
 to produce energy.

             On the Moon        49

the fence. We heard it land with a dull thud on the stony ground of 
the Moon. The sound reached us not by way of the air, but under the 
ground: the blow was carried by the ground's vibration, then by our 
bodies into the fine bones of our ears. By this path we could often hear 
the blows we had struck.
 "Could that be the way we hear each other?"
 "Hardly! The sound couldn't resonate the way it would in the air." 
 The ease of our movements awakened a most powerful desire to 
climb and jump.
 The sweet time of childhood! I remember how I would get up on 
the roof and trees, just like the cats or birds. That was pleasant...
 And the competitive leaps across the tape and over ditches! And 
running for prizes! I loved that passionately...
 Shouldn't I remember the old days? I had little strength, especially 
in my arms. I jumped and ran fairly well, but I had trouble climbing a 
rope or a pole.
 I used to dream of great physical strength: I would pay back my 
enemies and reward my friends! A child and a wild savage are the same 
Now those dreams of muscular strength seemed funny to me... All the 
same my desires, so ardent in my childhood, had become real here: it 
was as if my powers were increased sixfold thanks to the Moon's puny 
gravity.
  Besides that, here I didn't need to overcome the weight of my own 
body, which increased the effects of my strength even more. What was 
a fence for me here? No more than a threshold or a footstool that I 
could step over on Earth. And there, as if to prove this thought, we 
sailed upward and we flew over the fence without a running start. Then 
we jumped up and even leapt over the shed, but for that we needed a 
running start. And how pleasant it was to run: you didn't feel your legs 
beneath you. Off we went... who could beat the other? At a gallop!
  Every time our heels hit the ground we flew a few sazhens, 
especially horizontally. Wait! The whole yard, five hundred sazhens, 
in one minute: the speed of a race horse...
  Your "giant steps" don't allow you to make such leaps!

50          Red Star Tales

 We made measurements: at a gallop, even a fairly gentle one, we 
rose about four arshins above the ground; we moved along the ground 
five sazhens or more, depending on the speed of our pace.
 "Time for some gymnastics!"
 Hardly tensing our muscles, and even, for our own amusement,
using only our left hands, we climbed up the rope to the platform.
 Strange: four sazhens above the ground! It kept seeming as if we 
were on the clumsy Earth! Our heads were spinning...
 With a sinking heart I was the first to dare to jump down. I'm 
flying... Ouch! I hurt my heel a bit!
 I should have warned my friend about that, but I slyly encouraged 
him to jump. I lifted my head and shouted to him, "Jump, it easy — 
you won't hurt yourself!"
 "You're urging me for nothing: I know very well that jumping from 
here is the same as a two-arshin jump on the Earth. Of course you'll 
feel it a bit in your heels!"
 My friend flew down too. A slow flight... especially at first. The 
whole thing lasted about five seconds.
 In that much time you can think of a lot of things.
 "So what do you think, my physicist?"
 "My heart is beating — that's all."
 "To the garden! To climb the trees, to run through the alleys!" 
 "Why haven't the leaves dried out there?"
 Fresh green... protection from the Sun. Tall lindens and birches! 
Like squirrels, we leapt and climbed on the slender branches, and 
they didn't break. But of course — here we weren't any heavier than fat 
turkeys!
 We glided above the shrubbery and between the trees, and our 
movements recalled flight. Oh, it was fun! How easy it was to keep 
your balance here! If you tipped on a branch, ready to fall, the pull 
downwards was so weak, the tip off balance so slow, that the slightest 
movement of an arm or leg was enough to restore it.
 To the open spaces! The huge yard and garden seemed like a cage... 
At first we ran over the flat area. We came upon shallow trenches, up

                      On the Moon

to ten sazhens across. We flew across them at a run, like birds. But 
the climb had started; at first it was gradual, then steeper and steeper. 
What an incline! I was afraid I'd run out of breath.
  There was no need to fear: we went upward freely, with broad and 
rapid strides up the slope. The mountain was high — even the easy 
Moon exhausted us. We sat down. Why was it so soft here? Had the 
stones been softened?
  I picked up a big rock and struck it against another; sparks scattered. 
  "We're rested. Time to go back..."
  "How far is the house?"
  "Not far now, about two hundred sazhens."
  "Can you throw a rock that far?"
  "I don't know, try!"
  We each picked up a medium-sized sharp-cornered stone... Who 
could throw it farther? My stone went over our residence. And a good 
thing. Following its trajectory, I was afraid it would break a window.
  "And yours? Yours went even farther!"
  Shooting here would be interesting: bullets and cannonballs ought 
to fly for hundreds of versts horizontally and vertically.
  "But would gunpowder work here?"
  "Explosive materials in a vacuum ought to express themselves with 
even greater force than in an atmosphere, since the air only interferes 
with their expansion. As far as oxygen is concerned, they don't need it, 
 because they already contain the necessary amount."


                            fll
  We came home.
  "I'll sprinkle some gunpowder on the windowsill in the light of the 
 Sun," I said. "Use a magnifying glass to focus light on it... See — fire... 
 an explosion, even though it's a silent one." The familiar scent, which 
 dissipated in a moment.
   "You can fire a shot. Just don't forget to put on a firing cap: the 
 magnifying glass and the Sun will replace the blow of the hammer."

72           Red Star Tales

                VI
 The moon sank lower and lower, illuminating us and the lunar 
landscape more weakly and then more strongly, depending on which 
side was turned towards us — the watery one or the land one, or on how 
much of its atmosphere was full of clouds.
 There came a time when it touched the horizon and began to sink 
behind it — that meant we had reached the other hemisphere, invisible 
from Earth.
 About four hours later it disappeared completely, and we saw 
only the heights that it still illuminated. But they too went dim. The 
darkness was remarkable. A multitude of stars! You can see that many 
on Earth only with a decent telescope.
 Their lifelessness, however, is unpleasant; their motionlessness is
far from the motionlessness of the blue sky of tropical countries. 
 And the black background was so oppressive!
 What was that, giving off such a strong light in the distance?
 Half an hour later we found that it was the mountain peaks. More 
and more such peaks were beginning to glow.
 We had to run up the mountain. Half of it was lit up. There was the 
Sun! But while we ran up, the peak had already had time to grow dark, 
and the Sun was no longer visible from it.
 Apparently, this was the line of sunset.
 We set off more quickly. We flew like arrows from the bow.
 We could have hurried less than that: all the same we would see the 
Sun rising in the west, even if we ran only 5 versts per hour, that is, if 
we didn't run at all — what kind of a run is that! — but walked.
  But we couldn't help rushing.
 And there, 0 miracle!
  The rising star gleamed in the west. Its size quickly increased... 
A whole slice of the Sun was visible... The whole Sun! It rose, grew 
separate from the horizon... Higher and higher!
  However, that was only for us, because we were running; the 
mountaintops left behind us were going dark one by one.

              On the Moon        73

  If we hadn't looked at those unmoving shadows, the illusion would 
have been complete.
  "Enough, we're tired!" the physicist cried jokingly to the Sun. "You 
can go off and rest."
  We sat down and waited for the moment when the Sun, setting in 
the ordinary way, would disappear before our eyes.
  "Finita la (=media!"
  We turned over and fell soundly asleep.
  When we woke up we chased down the Sun again, just for the sake 
of warmth and light, without rushing, and we no longer let it out of our 
sight. It would rise and then sink, but it was constantly in the sky and 
warmed us without ceasing. We would fall asleep when the Sun was 
fairly high. As we woke up the laggard Sun would be crawling towards 
setting, but we would tame it in time and force it to rise again. We were  
approaching the pole!
  Here the Sun was so low and the shadows so enormous that, as 
we ran across them, we got properly chilled. In general, the contrast 
in temperature was striking. Some elevated places were heated up to 
the point where we couldn't even approach. We couldn't run through 
other places, which had been lying in the shade for fifteen days or more 
(earth time), without the risk of getting rheumatism. Don't forget that 
here the Sun, even though it was lying on the horizon, heated the rock 
surfaces no more weakly, but rather twice as strongly, as the Sun on 
Earth when it stands directly overhead. Of course, this can't be so in 
Earth's polar countries, because in the first place the power of the Sun's 
 ays is almost entirely absorbed by the thickness of the atmosphere. In 
 the second place, they don't shine on you so stubbornly at the pole: 
 every twenty four hours the Sun and its light go around any rock in a 
 circle, though they never let it out of sight.
  You'll say, "But what about heat conductivity? Shouldn't the heat 
 pass from a rock or mountain into the cold, stony ground?" I'll reply, 
 "Sometimes it does seep away, when the ground forms one whole 
 with the main mass, but many granite massifs are simply cast onto the 
 ground, regardless of their size, and only touch it or some other massif

             74                                           Red Star Tales

             at three or four points. Through these points the heat passes extremely 
             slowly, or better — imperceptibly. But the mass keeps heating up more 
             and more; the rate of radiation of the rays is so slow."
                  We had trouble, though, not with these heated stones, but with the 
             very chilled valleys that were lying in shadow. They interfered with 
             our approach to the pole because the closer we came to it the more 
             extensive and impenetrable the shadowed spaces were.
                  If only the seasons of the year were more noticeable here — but there 
             were hardly any seasons: in summer the Sun doesn't rise higher than 
             five degrees at the pole, while on Earth it rises five times higher.
                  And anyway, how long would we have to wait for summer, which 
             would, most likely, allow us more or less to reach the pole?
                  And so, moving along in the same direction after the Sun and 
             tracing a circle or, more accurately, a spiral on the Moon, we once 
             again moved farther from the point that's frozen in places with hot 
             rocks scattered over it.
                  We didn't want to freeze or to burn up either! We moved farther 
             and farther... It was hotter and hotter... We were forced to move away 
             from the Sun. We were forced to lag behind it, to keep from being 
             roasted. We ran in the dark, decorated at first by a few shining peaks 
             of mountain ranges. But then they were already gone. It was easier to 
             run: we'd already eaten and drunk a lot.
                  Soon the moon, which we had forced to move in the sky, would 
             appear.
                  There it was.
                   We greet you, o dear Earth!
                  We were glad to see it, no joke.
             long!And how could we not be! We had been separated from it for so 
                  Many more hours passed. Though we'd never seen those places 
              and mountains, they didn't attract our curiosity and they seemed 
              monotonous. We were tired of everything — all these wonders! Our 
              hearts were breaking, our hearts were aching. The view that was so 
              splendid but inaccessible from Earth only exacerbated the pain of


'                      ' '                 •           •                 4),7,,, • .

              On the Moon        75

recollections, the sores of unrecoverable losses. It would have been 
good at least to reach our residence as quickly as possible! We couldn't 
sleep! But what awaited us there, in the house? Well-known but 
 nanimate objects, able to prick and lacerate our hearts even more.
  From where did this longing arise? Before we had barely felt it. 
Hadn't it been overshadowed then by our interest in the surroundings, 
which hadn't yet had time to bore us by the novelty?
  Home as fast as possible, so at least we couldn't see those dead stars 
and that sky, black as mourning!
  Our residence had to be close by. It was here, we'd established it 
with astronomical observations, but 'despite indubitable indices we 
not only couldn't find the familiar yard — we didn't recognize even 
a single familiar view, a single mountain, which ought to have been 
familiar to us.
  We walked along and searched for it.
  Was it here, or there!? It was nowhere.
  We sat down in despair and fell asleep.
  The cold woke us up.
  We restored ourselves with some food; there wasn't much left. 
  We'd have to save ourselves from the cold by running.
  As if on purpose, we didn't come across a single suitable crevice 
where we could shelter from the cold.
  Again we ran after the Sun. Running like slaves, chained to a chariot! 
Running forever!
  Oh, far from forever. We had only enough food left for one meal. 
  What then?

  The meal was eaten, the last meal!
  Sleep closed our eyes. The cold forced us to huddle together like 
 brothers embracing.
  And where were all those crevices that kept showing up when we 
 didn't need them?

76          Red Star Tales

 We didn't sleep for long: the cold, still more powerful, woke us. 
Unceremonious and merciless! It hadn't let us sleep for even three 
hours. Hadn't let us get a good rest.
 Powerless, weakened by longing, hunger and the advancing cold, 
we couldn't run with our previous speed.
 We were freezing!
 Sleep started to overcome me first — and the physicist supported his 
friend, and then sleep started in on him — and I supported him against 
sleep, deadly sleep. The physicist had taught me to understand the 
meaning of this terrible, final drowsiness.
 We held each other up and gave each other strength. As I recall now, 
we didn't even think of abandoning each other and thus postponing 
the hour of our own deaths.
 The physicist was falling asleep and raving about the Earth; I 
hugged him, trying to warm his body with my own.
 I was overcome by tempting daydreams: about a warm bed, about 
the fire in a hearth, food and wine... I was surrounded by my own 
family... They were taking care of me, feeling sorry for me... They 
were taking me...

 Daydreams, daydreams! The blue sky, snow on the neighbors' 
roofs... A bird flew by... Faces, familiar faces... A doctor... What was 
he saying?
 "Lethargy, extended sleep, a dangerous situation... Significant 
weight loss... He's gotten much thinner... But he'll be all right! His 
breathing has improved... His responsiveness is returning... The crisis  
is passed."
 Everyone around was happy, despite their tear-stained faces...
 To make this brief, I had slept a diseased sleep and now I was awake: 
I lay down on the Earth and woke up on the Earth; my body remained 
here, while my thoughts flew off to the Moon.
 Nevertheless I raved for a long time: I asked about the physicist, 
spoke about the Moon, was surprised that my friends had come to

              On the Moon        77

be near me. I confused the earthly with the heavenly: first I imagined 
myself on Earth, then I was back on the Moon.
 The doctor ordered them not to argue with me and irritate me... 
 "hey were afraid I'd go crazy.
 Very slowly I returned to consciousness and even more slowly 
!::,legained my health.
 It goes without saying that the physicist was very surprised when, 
after I got better, I told him this whole story. He advised me to write it 
down and supplement,it with some explanations.

                      First published in Russian: 1893 
                      Translation by Sibelan Forrester

