ARKADY AND BORIS STRUGATSKY
                           1958














      THE SPONTANEOUS REFLEX
 Urm had gotten bored.
 Strictly speaking, boredom, as a reaction to uniformity and 
monotonous surroundings or an internal dissatisfaction — a loss of 
interest in life — is intrinsic only to humans and certain animals. In 
order to be bored, one needs, so to speak, a means of being bored: a 
finely and perfectly organized nervous system. One needs to be able to 
think, or at least to suffer. Urm did not have a nervous system in the 
usual sense of the word, and he was not able to think, let alone suffer. 
He only perceived, remembered, and acted. But just the same, he had 
gotten bored.
 The thing was that, after the Master had left, there was nothing new 
around for Urm to remember. Add to this the fact that the accumulation 
of new impressions was the basic stimulus that directed Urm's actions 
and motivated him to said actions. He was driven by an inexhaustible 
curiosity, an inexhaustible thirst to perceive and remember as much as

254          Red Star Tales

possible. If there were no unknown facts and phenomena, then some 
had to be found.
  But Urm's surroundings were familiar to him to the last visual detail, 
to the last undertone. He remembered the vast square room with 
rough cement walls, low ceiling, and iron door from the first moment 
of his existence. It always smelled here of heated metal and transformer 
oil. An indistinct low hum could be heard from somewhere above. 
People could not hear it without special instruments, but Urm heard it 
perfectly well. The fluorescent lights on the ceiling were extinguished, 
but just the same Urm saw the room perfectly well in infrared and in 
the pulse signals of his locators.
  And so, Urm had gotten bored, and he resolved to set out in search 
of new impressions. A half-hour had passed since the Master had gone. 
Experience suggested to Urm that he would not return anytime soon. 
This was very important, because Urm had once embarked on a little 
stroll around the room without having been ordered to do so, and the 
Master, who caught him in this activity, made it so that Urm could not 
even move his locator horn. Now, it seemed he did not have to worry 
about this.
  Urm teetered and heavily stepped forward. The cement floor rang 
out under his thick rubber soles, and Urm stopped for a moment to 
listen, and even bent over. But in the range of sounds emitted by the 
vibrating cement there was not a single new one, and Urm again made 
for the opposite wall. He walked right up to it and took a sniff. The 
wall smelled of wet concrete and rusted metal. Nothing new Then 
Urm turned around, gouging the wall with his sharp steel elbow, 
cut diagonally across the room and stopped in front of the door. 
Opening the door was not a simple matter, and Urm did not grasp 
right away how it should be done. Then, extending his toothed claw 
of a left hand, he nimbly grabbed the lock lever and turned it. The 
door opened with a weak, drawn-out groan. This was diverting, and 
Urm spent several minutes opening and closing the door, now quickly, 
now slowly, listening closely and committing the sounds to memory. 
Then he stepped across the high threshold and found himself facing

           The Spontaneous Reflex 255

a staircase. The staircase was narrow, with stone steps to the first 
landing, and fairly long. Urm in an instant counted eighteen steps to 
the first landing, where a light was burning. Then, taking his time, 
he went up. From the landing another staircase led upward, wooden, 
with ten steps, and a wide corridor opened to the right. Hesitating for 
a moment, Urm turned right. He did not know why. The corridor was 
no less interesting than the stairs. But it is probable that Urm did not 
like the look of the wooden steps.
  Warmth emanated from the corridor, and it was brightly illuminated 
in infrared. The infrared light was being emitted by some ribbed 
cylinders, mounted not far above the floor. Urm had never before seen 
steam radiators, and the ribbed cylinders interested him. He bent over 
and hooked one of them with both claws. A brief crack rang out along 
with the groaning of metal, and a thick cloud of hot steam swelled 
up to the ceiling. A stream of boiling water gushed under Urm's feet. 
Urm raised the cylinder up to his head, attentively looked it over, and 
examined the torn edge of the pipe. Then the cylinder was cast aside, 
and Urm's soles squelched through the puddles. Urm went to the end 
of the corridor. There above the low door blazed a red sign. "Caution! 
No Entry Without Protective Suit!" Urm read. He knew the word 
"caution," but also knew that this word always applied to people. To 
him, to Urm, this word could not apply. He extended his arm and gave 
the door a shove.
  Yes, here there was a great deal that was interesting and new. He 
stood in the entrance to a vast room, filled with objects of metal, stone, 
and plastic. In the middle of the room, a meter above the floor, rose a 
round concrete structure resembling a low pillar, covered with a shield 
of iron or lead. Numerous cables ran from it in all directions toward the 
walls, along which stretched marble panels with gleaming instruments 
and switch handles. An enclosure made of copper wire surrounded the 
concrete pillar, and gleaming articulated rods hung from the ceiling. 
The rods ended in pincers and claws, just like the ones on Urm's arms.
  Urm, treading inaudibly across the ceramic tiles of the floor, walked 
up to the copper meshwork and made a circuit around it. Then he

256          Red Star Tales

stood for a moment and walked around it a second time. There was 
no opening in the meshwork. Then Urm lifted his foot and effortlessly 
strode through the meshwork. Torn shreds of copper cobweb hung 
from his shoulders. But, before he took the two steps to the concrete 
pillar, he stopped stock-still. His head, round as a schoolroom globe, 
warily turned right and left: the ebonite shells of his acoustic receptors 
extended and stirred, his locator horns shuddered. The leaden lid on 
the pillar emitted infrared light, apparent even in the heated building. 
But, in addition to this, it was emitting some sort of ultra-radiant 
emanation. Urm saw well in x- and gamma rays, and it seemed to 
him that the lid was transparent, with a narrow concrete well opening 
under it, filled with glowing dust. In the depths of Urm's memory a 
command surfaced: leave this place at once. Urm did not know when and 
by whom this command had been issued. Probably, Urm came into the 
world already knowing it, as he knew many other things. But Urm did 
not obey the command. Curiosity turned out to be stronger. He bent 
over the pillar, extended his claws and with some effort lifted the lid.
 The flood of gamma rays blinded him. Red lights on the marble 
panels blinked on, and a siren began howling. He saw for a moment, 
through the transparent silhouettes of his arms, the interior of the 
concrete pit, then threw the lid down, proclaiming in a low, hoarse 
voice:
 "Opasnost! Gefahr! Danger! Weixian! Abunai!"
 A booming echo bounded around the room and faded away. Urm 
turned the upper portion of his body one hundred and eighty degrees 
and hastily made for the exit. The shock in his status meters brought 
about by the flood of radioactive particles drove him away from the 
concrete pillar. Of course, neither the hardest radiation nor a mighty 
flood of particles could do Urm the slightest harm; even spending 
some time in the active zone of a reactor would not threaten Urm with 
serious consequences. But, in creating Urm, his masters had embedded 
in him a tendency to stay as far away as possible from sources of intense  
radiation. Urm went out into the corridor, painstakingly closed the 
door behind him, and, stepping over the ribbed cylinder of the radiator,

           The Spontaneous Reflex 257

once again found himself on the staircase landing. Right away he saw a 
Human hurriedly coming down the wooden staircase.
  The Human was considerably shorter than the Master. It had on 
loose-fitting, light-colored clothing, and its hair was strangely long, 
and golden in color. Urm had never seen such people before. He drew 
in some air and sensed the familiar smell of white lilac. At times the 
Master gave off the same scent, though much more faintly.
  Half-darkness reigned on the landing, and the staircase behind the 
woman was brightly illuminated, so she could not immediately discern 
the outline of Urm's enormous body. Rather, hearing his footsteps, she 
stopped and called out angrily:
  "Who's that? It is you, Ivashev?"
  "Hello, how do you do?" said Urm huskily.
  The woman screamed. From the half-darkness a gleaming head 
with bulging glass eyes, excessively wide armor-plated shoulders, and 
thick articulated arms advanced on her. Urm set foot on the lowest 
step of the wooden staircase, and the woman began shrieking again.
  Never before had a Human failed to answer Urm's greeting. But 
this strange, high sound, shrill, penetrating and certainly inarticulate, 
did not resemble any of the standard answer templates that Urm 
knew. Intrigued, Urm purposefully moved forward after the retreating 
woman. The wooden steps groaned and cracked under his feet.
  "Back!" screamed the woman.
  Urm stopped and tilted his head, listening closely.
  "Back, you monster!"
  The command "back" was familiar to Urm. According to this 
 command, he was to turn the upper portion of his body around 
 and take several steps in the opposite direction until he heard the 
 command "stop." But commands usually originated from the Master, 
 and, besides that, Urm wanted to investigate. He once again began to 
 ascend the steps, until he found himself in front of the entrance of a 
 small, brightly lit room.
  "Back! Back! Back!" screamed the woman.

258           Red Star Tales

 By now Urm did not stop anymore, though he was going slower 
than he might. The room interested him: two desks, chairs, a drafting 
board, a bookcase, and thick folders. While he opened drawers, untied 
the strings on the folders and read aloud the notes that had been 
made in black ink in the margins of technical diagrams, the woman 
slipped into the room next door, hid behind the couch and grabbed the 
telephone handset. Urm saw this, as he had an optical receptor on the 
back of his head, but the small longhaired human no longer interested 
him. Walking across the papers spread all over the floor, he set of on 
his way. Behind his back the woman shouted into the telephone:
 "Nikolai Petrovich! Nikolai Petrovich, it's me, Galya! Nikolai 
Petrovich, Urm broke into our office. Your Urm! Urm! Uniform, 
Romeo, Mike... Didn't you hear the siren? Yes! I don't know... When 
I ran into him he was coming out of the big reactor room... Yes, yes, he 
was in the reactor room... What? Apparently not. They already know 
about it at the central station."
 Urm did not bother to listen. He went into the foyer and there 
stopped stock-still, redoubling the movements of his black locator 
horns. Something large, gleaming, and cold hung on the opposite wall. 
It seemed in infrared to be a grey, impenetrable square, and it flashed 
and shone silver in ordinary light, but this was not what confused Urm. 
In the strange square stood a black monstrosity with wiggling horns on 
its head, which was round like a schoolroom globe, and Urm could not 
understand just where it was located. His visual diastimeter instantly 
informed him that it was twelve meters, eight centimeters to the 
unfamiliar object, but his locator negated this report. There is no object 
there. There is a smooth, nearly vertical surface at a distance of.. six meters, 
four centimeters. Urm had never before seen the like, and his locator 
and his visual receptors had never before given him such contradictory 
readings. At the beginning of his existence a desire had been inlaid in 
his very physical being to make everything he happened to come into 
contact with clear and understood. So he resolutely walked forward, 
noting and recording on the way the relation that had emerged: "The 
distance according to the visual diastimeter is equal to the distance

                                                                                                 The Spontaneous Reflex                                                                                                                                                                            259

according to the locator, divided by two"... He walked into the mirror. 
The glass flew apart in a clangorous rain of shards, and Urm, leaning 
against the wall, stopped. Clearly, there was nothing left to do here. 
Urm scraped at the wall, sniffed, turned; paying no attention to the 
police officer on duty who, white as a sheet, was hanging from the lever 
of the air-raid siren, and, crunching through broken glass, he strode 
towards the exit. The driving snow surrounded him.

              As Nikolai Petrovich was throwing down the handset, Piskunov was 
already in the entryway, hurriedly buttoning his fur coat.
              "Where are you going?"
              "There, of course..."
              "Wait, we have to decide what to do. If that hunk of metal starts 
horsing around in the electrical station..."
              "It'll be fine if it's just the electrical station, " Ryabkin interrupted 
him. "What about the lab? Or the warehouse? Or what if he drops by 
over here, in the village?"
              Nikolai Petrovich was thinking intensely. Piskunov shifted 
impatiently from one foot to the other, holding onto the doorknob.
              "We have to run over there all together," gingerly suggested 
Kostenko, "Find him and... well, grab him!"
              Piskunov just winced, while Ryabkin, rooting around the rack in 
search of his fur coat, shouted angrily, "That's a great idea: grab him! 
What do you think we should grab him by? His pants? He weighs 
half a ton, one of his fists can punch with a force of three thousand 
kilos. It's ridiculous. You're new here, Kostenko, so you should just 
keep quiet...""Everybody listen," said Korolev. "Here's what we'll do.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  call
the dorm and raise the student trainees. You, Ryabkin, run to the 
motor pool... Dammit, everyone is probably at the club... Run over 
there anyway, find at least three drivers. We have to get the tracked 
bulldozers... Is that right, Piskunov?"
              "Yes, yes, and as soon as possible. But..."

260         Red Star Tales

 "Piskunov, you get over to the Institute. Figure out where Urm is 
and call the motor pool right away. Kostenko, you go with him. Clear?  
I just hope that devil doesn't get through the gate!"
 Jostling and stepping on each other's feet, they tumbled out onto 
the porch. Ryabkin slipped and butted his head into Kostenko's back, 
and Kostenko fell on all fours with a crash.
 "Dammit, just dammit!"
 "What, your glasses?"
 "No, everything's fine."
 A fierce wind drove clouds of dry snow over the ground, mournfully 
howled in the power lines, and hummed deeply in the iron lacework of 
the high-voltage towers. Dim rectangles of light fell from the windows 
of the cottage, and all else was plunged into impenetrable darkness.
 "Well, I'm off," said Ryabkin. "Be careful over there, friends, don't 
stick your necks out if you don't have to."
 He stumbled again and for a minute floundered in the snowdrift, 
muttering obscene obscenities at the damned snowstorm, that pig of an  
Urm and generally all those accessory to the incident. Then his light- 
colored fur coat was glimpsed by the wicket gate before it disappeared 
in the eddies of swirling snow.
 Piskunov and Kostenko were left alone.
 Kostenko huddled up against the bitter cold.
 "I don't understand," he said. "What on earth are the tractors for?"  
 "And what would you recommend?" inquired Piskunov.
 "No, I just don't understand... Do you want to destroy Urm?" 
 Piskunov exhaled sharply.
 "Urm is a unique machine, the creative result of the last several 
years of work by the Institute of Experimental Cybernetics. Do you 
understand? Why would I want him destroyed?"
 He lifted up the tails of his fur coat and made his way through the 
snowdrift. A confused and timid Kostenko followed after him. The 
snow-covered field lay before them, the highway behind them. Right 
across the highway was the electrical station.

          The Spontaneous Reflex 261

 So as to shorten their path, Piskunov turned off of the highway and 
went through the vacant lot where a foundation pit had been excavated 
in the fall for a new building. Kostenko could hear Piskunov muttering 
something as he stumbled over an ice-covered pile of bricks and rods 
of rebar. It was difficult going. Beyond the shroud of the snowstorm 
they could just make out the Institute's sparse chain of lights.
 "Wait a second," Kostenko said finally. "By God, it's hard going! 
Let's rest for a minute."
 Piskunov squatted down next to him. What had happened, after 
all? He knew Urm like no one else at the Institute. Every little screw, 
every electrode, every lens of that marvelous mechanism had passed 
through his hands. He had thought he could calculate and predict each 
of his movements under any circumstances. And now this. Urm had 
"willfully" come out of his basement and was now strolling around the 
electrical station. Why?
 Urm's behavior was governed by his "brain," an extraordinarily 
complex and delicate apparatus composed of germanium-platinum 
foam and ferrite. While an ordinary digital machine has tens of 
thousands of circuits (the elementary parts that receive, store, and 
deliver information), Urm's brain employed nearly eighteen million 
logic cells. They held the programmed reactions for a multitude of 
situations, for different variations of changes in circumstances, and 
they anticipated the execution of an enormous number of different 
operations. What could have influenced the "brain," the program? 
Emissions from his atomic engine? No, his engine is surrounded by 
thick shielding made of zirconium, gadolinium, and boron steel. In 
practical terms, not a single neutron, not a single gamma ray could 
pierce the shielding. Then his receptors? No, the receptors had 
been in ideal working order just this evening. Then the whole of 
the matter is in the "brain" itself. The program. The complex new 
program. Piskunov himself had overseen the programming and... The 
programming... That was it!
 Piskunov stood up slowly.

262           Red Star Tales

  "A spontaneous reflex!" he said. "Of course, its a spontaneous 
reflex! I'm an idiot!"
  Kostenko looked at him fearfully.
  "I don't understand..."
  "But I do. It's obvious... But who would have thought? Everything 
was going so well."
  "Look!" Kostenko suddenly yelled.
  He gasped and jumped to his feet. The greyish-black sky over the 
Institute was lit up by a tremulous blue explosion, and against this blaze,  
surprisingly well defined and at the same time unreal, the silhouettes of 
black buildings sprang up out of the whirling of the snowstorm. The 
sparsely lit chain of lights that defined the walls of the Institute blinked 
and went out.
  "It's the transformer!" said Piskunov hoarsely. "The substation's 
right across from the reactor tower. That's were Urm is... and the 
guards..."
  "Let's run!" Kostenko proposed.
  They set off running. This was no simple matter. The oncoming 
wind swept them off of their legs, and they tripped in holes filled with 
dry snow, fell, got up, and fell again.
  "Faster, faster!" Piskunov urged.
  Tears, either from the wind or from the excitement, covered his 
face, froze on his eyelashes as blurry little drops of ice, made it hard 
for him to see. He grabbed Kostenko's arm and dragged him, still 
muttering hoarsely:
  "Faster, faster!"
  Apparently, the explosion over the Institute had been noticed in the 
village. On the outskirts, a siren began howling anxiously, the windows 
of the cottages where the guards were stationed lit up, and the blinding 
ray of a searchlight skimmed over the field. It plucked snowy barchans 
and the latticed pillars of the of the high-voltage towers out of the 
darkness, slid along the stone wall that surrounded the Institute, and, 
finally, came to a stop at the gate. Next to the gate small black figures 
moved around rapidly.

           The Spontaneous Reflex 263

 "Who's that... over there?" asked Kostenko, catching his breath.
 "The guards. The police, probably..." Piskunov stopped, wiped 
his eyes, his voice was failing him. "They've locked... the gate. Good 
thinking! That means... Urm's still over there."
 Apparently, the alarm had been raised. Now not one, but three 
searchlights were feeling along the walls of the Institute. One could 
see snowy whirlwinds dancing in the blue light. Through the noise and 
the wind's howling the sound of shouts reached them; someone was 
cursing angrily. Finally, motors roared to life, the clank of treads could 
be heard. The gigantic bulldozers were coming out of the vehicle fleet.
 "Look, Kostenko," said Piskunov. "Look closely. We are present at 
the most unusual round-up in the history of humanity. Look closely, 
Kostenko!"
 Kostenko looked skeptically at Piskunov. It seemed to him that tears 
were running down the engineer's face. Of course, they could have 
been from the wind.
 Meanwhile, they could now hear the clank of treads not only from 
behind, but also to the right. The bulldozers were on the highway. 
They could already see the shaky sparks of headlights. There were five 
such sparks.
 "Five against one," whispered Piskunov. "He doesn't have a chance. 
His spontaneous reflex arc won't help him here."
 And then something suddenly changed all around them. Kostenko 
could not even tell right away just what had happened. As before, the 
snowstorm howled; as before, clouds of dry snow tore around over the 
ground; as before, the motors of the bulldozers roared, threatening 
and confident. But the searchlights were no longer gliding along the 
field. They had come to a dead stop at the gate. But the gate was wide 
open, and no one was next to it.
 "What the devil?" said Kostenko.
 "Surely he didn't..."
 Piskunov did not finish, and, not bothering to consult one another, 
they set off running to the Institute. They were not two hundred 
meters from the gate when Piskunov, running in front, flew into a

264          Red Star Tales

man with a rifle. The man cried out in terror and was about to flee 
in another direction, but Piskunov grabbed him by the shoulders and 
stopped him.
 "What's happening?"
 The man crazily turned his head, clad in its police cap, swore, and 
finally came to his senses.
 "He broke out," he said. "He broke out. He pushed the gate over 
and left. Almost stomped on ivlakeyev. I'm heading into the village for 
back-up..."
  "Where did he go?"
 The police office waved to the left without conviction.
  "That way, I think... To the highway..."
  "That means he'll run into the tractors any minute. Let's go."
  They would remember what happened next for the rest of their 
lives. Out of the whirling snowy darkness something huge and formless 
came towards them, red and green blinking lights stung their eyes, and 
a sharp voice with no intonation pronounced,
  "Hello, how do you do?"
  "Urm, stop!" screamed Piskunov desperately.
  Kostenko saw the policeman run, saw Piskunov raise his arms and 
shake his fists. Then a monstrous figure, wreathed in steam, a baleful 
scarecrow, went past him, raising high its legs, thick as logs, and melted 
into the snowstorm.

  After carefully closing the door behind him, as he always did if the 
door was not broken, Urm took a step and stopped. Everything around 
him was full of sounds, movements, and emanations. He saw the night 
as a multicolored faery kaleidoscope of radio waves. Thirteen and a 
half meters in front of him was a squat building with wide windows, 
covered with iron grating. Its walls emitted bright infrared light. From 
the building he heard a low, powerful hum. A million snowflakes swirled 
around in the air. As they settled down on Urm's faceted sides, hot 
from the fire of his atomic engine, they instantly melted and vaporized,

           The Spontaneous Reflex 265

  Urm swiveled his head and decided that the nearest and most 
interesting object of study could only be the squat building across 
the way. He found the entrance immediately, noting a path on the 
downwind side. Low fir trees were planted all around the building, 
and pausing for a moment, he broke off one of them and examined it. 
Then he opened the door and went in.
  Two humans were sitting next to a table in the close, narrow little 
room. As he appeared they leapt up and stared at him in horror. He 
closed the door behind him (and even threw the bolt) and stopped 
before them.
  "How do you do?" he said.
  "Comrade Piskunov?" one of the humans asked in confusion. 
  "Comrade Piskunov has stepped out. Would you like to leave a 
message?" Urm informed him coolly.
  The humans did not interest him. His attention was drawn by a 
small, hairy creature that was cowering against the wall. Warn; alive, 
smells strongly, not a Human, determined Urm and said, "Hello, how 
do you do?"
  "Grrr..," answered the creature with a bravery born of despair, 
baring its sharp, white teeth and pressing still more firmly into the 
corner.
  Urm was absorbed by the dog and completely indifferent to the fact 
 that the policemen had deftly barricaded themselves behind the table 
 and filing cabinet and had begun to hurriedly undo their holsters.
  Whining piteously, with its tail between its legs, the little dog dashed 
 past Urm. But Urm was far more nimble than a dog. He was more 
 nimble than the most nimble animal in the world. His torso turned a 
 half circle in a lightning-quick and silent motion, and a long extending 
 arm, like a telescope, snatched the dog up by its side. At that moment 
 a shot rang out: one policemen's nerve had failed him. The bullet rang 
 off the armor that covered Urm's back, and ricocheted deep into the 
 wall. Plaster rained down.
  "Sidorenko, stop shooting!" yelled the other policeman.

266          Red Star Tales

 Urm released the quivering little dog and set his sights on the 
humans, pale but very resolute, holding their weapons at the ready. 
He sniffed the air with curiosity. The unfamiliar smell of smokeless 
gunpowder was diffusing in the air. The little dog cowered under the 
policemen's legs, but Urm had already lost interest in it. He turned 
and went to the next door, which was adorned with the image of a skull 
and crossbones pierced by a red lightning bolt. The policemen, struck 
dumb in wonderment, watched his clawlike fingers fumbling with the 
ribbed barrel of the lock. The door opened. Then they got a grip on 
themselves and both raced after him:
 "Stop! Get back! You can't!"
 They clung to his armored sides, grabbing his pillar-like legs, hot 
as a stove, forgetting everything in the world in terror at the single 
thought of what chaos this iron monster could wreak in the substation. 
But Urm simply did not notice them. Their efforts made no impression 
whatever on him; they may as well have been trying to stop a moving 
tractor. Then one of them, pushing his comrade aside, emptied his 
entire magazine into Urm's head, point-blank, from below. The 
substation chamber, flooded with light, rang with the din of gunshots.
 Urm reeled. The ebonite shell of his right acoustic receptor flew 
apart in splinters. His crooked locator horn broke loose and hung 
there, dangling on a wire. The sound of broken glass rang from the 
ceiling.
 Urm had never before been subjected to an attack. He lacked 
an instinct for self-preservation and had no experience fighting 
with humans. But Urm could put facts together, could make logical 
conclusions and choose a behavior path that maximally ensured his 
safety. All these mental operations took him a fraction of a second. In  
the next moment he turned around and started towards the humans, 
threateningly displaying his terrible claws.
 The policemen split up. One ran behind the panelboard, and the 
other leapt behind the massive steel housing of the closest transformer, 
hurriedly reloading his pistol.

            The Spontaneous Reflex 267

  "Sidorenko! Run to the watchman's booth, call them, raise the 
alarm!" he shouted.
  But Sidorenko had no success in running to the door. Urm moved 
far faster than a human, and the moment the policeman came out 
from behind the panelboard, Urm took two steps and stood before 
him. Then the humans resolved to run out simultaneously. This, too, 
was unsuccessful: Urm zipped from the panelboard to the transformer 
with the speed of an express train.
  The panelboard broke in half from Urm's ungainly lunging, the 
wind whistled through the bullet holes in the windows and the glass 
ceiling.
  Finally, Urm got tired of that game, and he resolved to leave the 
humans in peace. He stopped suddenly in front of the transformer and 
decisively thrust his hands under the housing. The policemen took 
this opportunity to go hurtling headlong to the watchman's booth. At 
the same instant, a deafening crack rang out, everything around was lit 
up by a blinding blue flash, and the lights when out. The acrid smell 
of burnt metal, smoke, and hot varnish poured out of the room. The 
deafened, dispirited policemen did not comprehend right away what 
had happened. And then the watchman's booth shivered from heavy 
footsteps, and a reedy voice pronounced in the darkness:
  "Hello, how do you do?"
  The door bolt clicked, and the door opened with a creak. For a 
moment the outline of the iron monster could be seen in the dim 
rectangle, and the door closed once again.
  Urm walked around the grounds of the Institute, sinking into the 
snow and lifting his legs high. The Institute was plunged in darkness, 
and darkness offered little to help even Urm's infrared vision. He could 
make out only the weak radiance around his stomach and legs, on 
which snowflakes melted and vaporized. A few weakly phosphorescent 
human silhouettes could be glimpsed between the buildings. Urm paid 
no attention to them and went along, orienting himself by locator 
readings — though one locator horn had been smashed by the bullet, 
making it impossible for him to determine distances correctly.

268          Red Star Tales

 The faraway lights of the village, barely visible gleams through the 
snowstorm, drew Urm's attention. Then the bright blue rays of the 
searchlights blazed on. He went up to the wall, hesitated for a moment 
and turned left, He was well aware that walls always have doors. And 
before long he ended up at the gate. It was a large gate, made of iron.  
The main thing, though, was that it was locked. On the other side of 
the gate he could hear the alarmed voices of the humans; a bright blue 
light pierced through the chink.
 "Hello," said Urm, and heaved at the gate. The gate did not give 
way: it was firmly locked. From somewhere far away he could hear the 
clank of metal. There, beyond the gate, something very interesting was 
taking place. Urm pressed harder, then stepped away, threw back his 
head and struck the gate at a run with his armored chest. The voices 
beyond the gate fell silent, and then someone yelled uncertainly:
 "Back! Hey, careful you don't shoot that devil!"
 "Hello, how do you do?" said Urm, ran back and struck again. The 
gate collapsed. The bolt turned out to be stronger than the hinges built 
into the concrete wall, and the gate fell flat as a plank onto the snow. 
Urm walked over it past the scattered policemen and plunged into the 
snowstorm that was raging in the open field.
 He marched onward, continuously struggling to recover his balance 
on the dug-up earth covered by a swelling sea of dry snow. Suddenly, 
an emptiness opened up beneath him, and he fell. The snow sizzled 
underneath him. He had never fallen before, but an instant later he 
had already dug his hands into the earth, extended them to their full 
length, and drew his legs up under him.
 He regained his footing and stood for a moment, looking about. 
The lights of the cottages gleamed before him. To the left, very close 
by, loomed three human figures; further away vehicles growled, 
moving towards the gates in a line. Urm turned to the left. Going past 
the humans, he recognized one of them as the Master. The Master 
could deprive him of his ability to move. Urm remembered this very 
well and began to walk faster. The Master dropped out of sight behind 
him in the whirls of the shifting snow.

           The Spontaneous Reflex 269

  He emerged on a flat place where the snow was plowed smooth. 
A bright light illuminated him from head to foot. Unwieldy metal 
monsters, carrying heavyshields before them, moved towards him and 
came to a stop, snorting angrily.
  Urm stood five steps from the lead bulldozer, slowly turning his 
round head to the right and to the left and repeating:
  "Hello, how do you do?"

  Nikolai Petrovich Korolev jumped down from the tractor. The 
driver yelled in a panic:
  "Comrade engineer, where are you going?"
  At that moment, Piskunov appeared on the highway. Disheveled, 
his hair standing on end (his fur hat was left behind somewhere in 
the vacant lot), his hands thrust deep into the pockets of his wide- 
open fur coat, he went around the bulldozer and stopped before Urm. 
There were not more than five steps between them. Urm loomed like 
a giant over the engineer, like a tower, his faceted sides gleamed in the 
headlights, his stomach, wreathed in steam, shone with moisture; his 
round head with its large glass eyes, splayed-out receptor ears, and 
locator horn resembled the frightful and ridiculous pumpkin masks 
that village boys use to scare girls. His head danced smoothly as his 
eyes followed Piskunov's every move.
  "Urm," said Piskunov loudly.
  Urm's head froze in place; his articulated arms were glued to his 
sides.
  "Urm, listen to my command!"
  Urtn answered:
  "I am ready."
  Someone laughed nervously.
  Piskunov stepped forward and placed his gloved hand on Urm's 
chest. His fingers quickly slid along the armor, feeling for what 
would settle the matter: the switch that linked the computational- 
analytic portion of Urm's brain to his power and movement system. 
And then something unexpected happened, unexpected for everyone

270          Red Star Tales

except Piskunov, who feared it more than anything. Apparently, Urm's 
memory had saved an association linking this movement by the Master 
to an instant inability to move. Piskunov's fingers had barely touched 
the key when Urm turned sharply. His armored hand cut through the 
air above the head of Piskunov, who just managed to duck, and Urm, 
in no rush, started back along the highway. Nikolai Petrovich was the 
first to come to his senses.
 "Hey, guys!" he yelled. "Bring the bulldozers around from the right 
and the left. Cut off his path to the gate... Piskunov, hey, Piskunov!"
 But Piskunov did not hear him. While the bulldozers crawled in 
both directions away from the highway, diving into the clouds of snow, 
he set off running after Urm.
 "Urm, stop!" he yelled in a high, breaking voice. "Stop, you brute! 
Come back! Back!"
 He ran out of breath. Urm was going ever faster, and the distance 
between them gradually widened. Finally, Piskunov stopped, shoved 
his hands into his pockets, and, drawing his head into his shoulders, 
watched him go. Nikolai Petrovich and Ryabkin ran up to him. 
Kostenko came up last.
 "What's gotten into you?" asked Korolev angrily.
 Piskunkov did not answer.
 "He's not obeying," he said. "You understand, Kolya? He's not 
obeying. It's clearly a spontaneous reflex,"
 Nikolai Petrovich nodded.
 "I was thinking the same thing."
 "Obviously!" exclaimed Piskunov. "You'd have the same degree of 
success letting a train pick its own time and itinerary..."
 "What's a spontaneous reflex?" asked Kostenko timidly.
 No one answered him.
 "And just the same, in spite of everything, this is really something." 
Nikolai Petrovich blew his nose and shoved his handkerchief into his 
inner pocket. "He's not obeying! Of all things..."
 "Let's go!" said Piskunov decisively.

           The Spontaneous Reflex 271

 Meanwhile, the bulldozers had spread out in a half-circle and began 
to converge around Urm, who was unhurriedly shuffling along the 
highway. One of the bulldozers crawled out onto the highway ahead 
of him, with its back end to the gate, another came up at him from 
behind, the remaining three approached from the sides: two from the 
left, one from the right. Of course, Urm had long since noticed that 
he was being surrounded, but he probably thought nothing of it. He 
continued moving along the highway until his chest ran up against the 
bulldozer. He pressed, the tractor teetered just a bit; the driver grabbed 
at the levers with a tense face. Urm took a step back and hit it at a run. 
Iron clanged against iron, and bright sparks could be seen cutting the 
snowy darkness under the straight beams of the headlights. At that 
moment the blade of the rear bulldozer hit Urm's back. Urm froze 
stock-still, only his head slowly turned on its axis, just like a school 
globe. From the right and left approached two more bulldozers and 
securely closed the remaining avenues of retreat. Urm found himself 
in captivity.
  "Comrade engineers! Comrade Piskunov! What should we do 
now?" yelled the driver of the first machine.
  "Comrade Piskunov has stepped out. Would you like to leave a 
message?" said Urm.
  He took a swing and struck the blade. Then he did so again and 
again. He hit steadily, like a boxer in a training session, knocked back 
slightly with every blow, and splashes of sparks hailed from under the 
clanging of his club-like hands.
  Piskunov, accompanied by Nikolai Petrovich, Ryabkin, and 
Kostenko, approached him.
  "We have to do something quickly, or he'll disable himself," said 
Ryabkin anxiously.
  Piskunov climbed without speaking onto the tread of the tractor, 
but Ryabkin grabbed him and pulled him back down.
  "What's the matter?" asked Piskunov with annoyance.

272          Red Star Tales

 "You're the only person who knows Urm intimately. If he lays you 
out... this whole thing could last for months. Someone else should do 
it."
 "He's right," said Nikolai Petrovich hastily. "I'll go."
 One of the workers who were standing around the engineers 
broke in:
 "Maybe you could choose one of us? We're younger, quicker..." 
 "I'll do it," said Kostenko somberly.
 "That won't work," said Nikolai Petrovich. "Don't let Piskunov 
go.
 He threw off his fur coat and climbed onto the tractor. Then 
Piskunov tore loose from Ryabkin's embrace.
 "Let me go, Ryabkin."
 Ryabkin did not answer. Kostenko approached from the other side 
and firmly gripped Piskunov by the shoulders.
 And Urm was raging. The lower half of his body was securely 
clamped by the bulldozers, but the upper part moved freely, and he 
turned from side to side with lightening speed, pounding the iron 
blades with backhanded blows of his steel fists. Shreds of steam circled 
above him in the snowy darkness. "The force of one blow of his fist is 
three thousand kilos," recalled Kostenko.
 Nikolai Petrovich, setting his teeth, squatted down between the 
bulldozers at Urm's feet and waited for the right moment. His ears 
hurt from the clanging and crashing. He knew that Urm had noticed 
him: the glass eyes, now and then glimmering warily, would turn to 
him.
 "Easy, easy," whispered Nikolai Petrovich soundlessly. "Easy, my 
dear Urm. Take it easy, you scoundrel!"
 Sonic sort of new sound arose amid the blows, something cracked, 
either Urm's steel hand or the blade of the bulldozer. There was no 
more time to delay. Nikolai Petrovich dove under Urm's fist and 
pressed up to his side. And then Urm surprised everyone. His arms fell 
to his sides. The crashing ceased, and once again they could hear the 
snowstorm howling over the field and the tractors snorting. Nikolai

           The Spontaneous Reflex  273

Petrovich, pale and sweating, straightened up and reached his hand to 
Urm's chest. A dry click rang out. The green and red lights on Urm's 
shoulders went out.
 "It's over," Piskunov croaked out and closed his eyes.
 People began talking right away in exaggeratedly loud voices; 
laughter and jokes could be heard. The drivers helped Nikolai 
Petrovich get out from under Urm and lowered him to the ground. 
Piskunov embraced and kissed him.
 "And now," he said abruptly, "to the Institute. We will work. It will 
take a week, a month... We'll have to beat this nonsense out of him 
and finally make him an Urm: a Universal Roving Machine.

 "But what was it that happened with Urm?" asked Kostenko. And 
what is a spontaneous reflex?"
 Nikolai Petrovich, tired and drawn after the sleepless night, said, 
"You see, Urm was constructed by order of the Department for 
Interplanetary Communications. He differs from other highly complex 
cybernetic machines in that he is intended for work in conditions that 
cannot be predicted by even the most ingenious programmer. On 
Venus, for instance. Who knows what the conditions are there? Maybe 
it is covered by oceans. But maybe by deserts. Or jungles. For the time 
being people cannot be sent there: it's too dangerous. Urms will be 
sent, dozens of Unns. But how should they be programmed? The 
trouble is that, at the current level of cybernetics, it is still impossible 
to teach a machine to 'think' abstractly..."
 "What do you mean?"
 "For a machine there is no general dog. There is only this one, that 
one, a third dog. If it meets a fourth dog that doesn't resemble the first 
three, the machine won't know what to do. Roughly speaking, if Unn 
is programmed for a definite reaction only in relation to a mutt, he will 
be unable to react the same way in relation to a pug. It's a simplistic 
example, of course, but I presume that you understand me. And this 
is one of the basic differences between the smartest machine and the 
dumbest person: an inability to operate in abstract categories. Anyway,

274          Red Star Tales

Piskunov attempted to compensate for this shortcoming by creating 
a self-programming machine. He gave Urm's 'brain' a reflex chain, 
the essence of which boils down to filling vacant memory cells in a 
self-governing fashion. Piskunov calculated that, once he "fills up on 
impressions," Urm will be capable of picking the most beneficial line 
of behavior for every new event. This is the most advanced model of 
consciousness in the world. But we got an unexpected result. Well, 
Piskunov had theoretically allowed for such a phenomenon, but in 
practice... To put it succinctly, the new reflex arc generated dozens of 
secondary reflexes not anticipated by the programmers. Piskunov has 
christened them spontaneous reflexes. With their appearance, Urm 
ceased to function according to his basic programming and began to 
`direct himself.'"
 "What do we need to do now?"
 "We'll try a different approach." Nikolai Petrovich stretched and 
yawned. "We will perfect the analytic capabilities of the 'brain,' the 
receptor system..."
 "But what about the spontaneous reflex? No one is interested in it?"
 "Oh, Piskunov has already thought something up... In a word, the 
first ones on unexplored planets and in unexplored oceans will still be  
Urms. We will not have to risk people... Listen, Kostenko, let's get 
some sleep, OK? You'll be working here and will learn everything, I 
give you my word."


                     First published in Russian: 1958 
                       Translation by Kevin Reese

                                                        MIKHAIL ANCHAROV          1961














                                  SODA-SUN

         The author of a hypothesis implicitly acknowledges the possibility 
         of a mistake, so that in the course of rigorous experimentation 
         the hypothesis can be overturned, verified, or transformed into 
         something different.
                                                        — Academician N. Semenov

         The richest ideas are the most specific and subjective ones. That 
         which is truly individual represents infinity in embryonic form.— V .1. Lenin

                             1. For What, Actually?
   They said that he wasn't serious, just chasing after 
sensations. As I left, I looked at him and thought that it 
was the other way around: he's very serious, because he 
seriously loves what is sensational. This was his position:

